<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="null"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
	
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Chapter 7: Lies in Writing</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p/>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note type="abstract">Sample abstract text</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc sameAs="http://www.cwrc.ca">
				<p>Created from original research by members of CWRC/CSÉC unless otherwise noted.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	<xenoData><rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:as="http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#" xmlns:cwrc="http://sparql.cwrc.ca/ontologies/cwrc#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:geo="http://www.geonames.org/ontology#" xmlns:oa="http://www.w3.org/ns/oa#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" xmlns:fabio="https://purl.org/spar/fabio#" xmlns:bf="http://www.openlinksw.com/schemas/bif#" xmlns:cito="https://sparontologies.github.io/cito/current/cito.html#" xmlns:org="http://www.w3.org/ns/org#"/></xenoData></teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="prose">
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p><ref target="#tgenreissue"><ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">Life writing</ref>,
						broadly construed, was at once one of the most welcoming and one of the most
						challenging genres for women writers in the nineteenth century.</ref> The
					nineteenth-century woman writer who planned to write about a life, whether her
					own or someone else’s, faced several challenges. Following <persName key="James Boswell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A88a01f90-9336-4c3b-85f5-032849180b89">James Boswell</persName>’s <title key="The Life of Samuel Johnson" ref="http://www.wikidata.org/entity/Q1218644">Life of Samuel Johnson</title>
					(1791), often cited as the first modern <ref target="#tgenre_biography">biography</ref>, biography began to coalesce as a genre in the nineteenth
					century. <ref target="#pattitudes">Writing a biography required education and
						training in scholarly methods, which many women writers lacked. Biography is
						rooted in research, and women writers were less likely to have both the
						education to undertake such research and the access to the manuscript and
						book materials that they needed for such work than their male counterparts.
						These challenges faced would-be woman biographers regardless of the gender
						of their proposed subject. <ref type="#tthemetopic">If a woman writer wanted
							to write the life of another woman, these same challenges were
							exacerbated: with the exception of Queens and other figures of
							historical import, women’s lives were not usually well-documented, and
							the would-be biographer of a woman who was not <persName key="Queen Elizabeth I" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5ac060d4-2d7e-4684-a2ab-537a0c86e4ba">Queen Elizabeth I</persName> faced the dual challenge of finding
							sources and writing about another woman’s life when many assumed that
							women’s lives were trivial and not worth documenting.</ref></ref><note type="scholarNote">Juliette Atkinson, <title level="m">Victorian Biography Reconsidered a Study of Nineteenth-Century “Hidden” Lives.</title> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2010), 146-147.</note> <ref type="#tgenreissue">Indeed, writing about a woman’s life could be seen as an
						unseemly invasion of her privacy; in his <title level="m">Memoirs of the
							Author of A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</title> (1798), <persName key="William Godwin" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8a4d5074-7c65-4376-a5c8-3f804adc1d16">William Godwin</persName> revealed <persName key="Mary Wollstonecraft" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:25504fac-570f-4fb6-bee5-73314bed90ae">Mary Wollstonecraft</persName>’s illegitimate daughter.</ref>
					<ref type="#tgenreissue">The potential for biography to invade women’s privacy
						was not helped by the fact that some of the most popular lives of women in
						the eighteenth century were the vies scandaleuses of courtesans like
							<persName key="Teresia Constantia Phillips" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:eabd259b-1fd7-4a83-9153-f6ada722f993">Teresia Constantia Phillips</persName> and <persName key="Laetitia Pilkington" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:850338f6-0641-471c-83e2-718d467a96c8">Laetitia Pilkington</persName>.</ref><note type="scholarNote">Frances
						Wilson, “Romantic Autobiography.” In The Cambridge Companion to
						Autobiography, edited by Maria DiBattista and Emily O. Wittman (New York:
						Cambridge UP, 2014), 71. See also Atkinson, Victorian Biography, 147.</note>
					<ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">Autobiography</ref>, a term that was coined
					at the end of the eighteenth century in 1797 and confidently used by 1809,<note type="scholarNote">Linda Peterson, Traditions of Victorian Women’s
						Autobiography: The Poetics and Politics of Life Writing, (Charlottesville:
						University of Virginia Press, 1999), 3.</note> developed alongside <ref target="#tgenre_biography">biography</ref>, and even women who sought to
					write about their own lives from their own perspective faced the notion that it
					was unseemly for women to centre themselves. The situation was more difficult
					for working class women writers, who tended to be less literate than both
					working class men and middle-class women, and who wrote, by one estimate, only
					one in ten working class <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographies</ref> in the period.<note type="scholarNote">For literacy,
						see Jane Rendall, “A Short Account of my Unprofitable Life”: Autobiographies
						of Working Class Women in Britain c. 1775-1845, In Women’s Lives / Women’s
						Times: New Essays on Auto/biography, edited by Trev Lynn Broughton and Linda
						R. Anderson (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1997), 32. For an
						overview of Victorian working class writing, see Florence Boos, Memoirs of
						Victorian Working-Class Women: The Hard Way Up (New York: Palgrave
						Macmillan, 2017), 2.</note> Very few of these were published in the
					nineteenth century, and over half of the extant working class women’s <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographies</ref> remain in
						manuscript.<note type="scholarNote">Boos, Memoirs of Victorian Working-Class
						Women, 2. Boos notes that a few more autobiographical writings of working
						class Victorian women have been uncovered since these numbers were
						calculated.</note>
					<ref target="#pnonsurvival">Indeed, not all women’s life writing survived:
							<persName key="Elizabeth Inchbald" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:b6be4731-d790-4e8a-9f8a-9d1c28455b3c">Elizabeth Inchbald</persName> worked for years writing her life’s story
						in the final years of her life, but encountered so many difficulties with
						publishers who were afraid that the book would be too scandalous or not
						scandalous enough, that she had the manuscript destroyed upon her
						death.</ref></p>
				<p>Despite the many challenges that nineteenth-century women writers faced in
					contributing to the development of biography and autobiography, there were also
					inroads into life writing more broadly speaking. Deeply researched <ref target="#tgenre_biography">single-subject biographies</ref> and <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">book-length autobiographies</ref> may have
					been the most prestigious forms of life writing, but there were other forms of
						<ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">life writing</ref> that were more
					accessible to women writers, in which they excelled. Nineteenth-century women,
					like the women that came before them, were often seen as the record-keepers of
					the family. For many women, it was a domestic duty to keep up correspondence
					with family and friends: some women, like <persName key="Jane       Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Jane Welsh Carlyle</persName>, turned <ref target="#tgenre_letter">letter
						writing</ref> into an art form and gained recognition for their literary
					talents well after their deaths. Material factors: including cheaper paper,
					rising literacy levels, and the introduction of the penny post (in 1840!) meant
					that letters became central to the organisation of everyday life.<note type="scholarNote">Donovan, Susan. “How the Post Office and Postal Products
						Shaped Mid-Nineteenth-Century Letter-Writing.” BRANCH: Britain,
						Representation and Nineteenth-Century History. Ed. Dino Franco Felluga.
						Extension of Romanticism and Victorianism on the Net. Web. February 24,
						2023. </note> Women writers also kept up <ref target="#tgenre_diary">diaries</ref> in large numbers; like their letters, many of these <ref target="#tgenre_diary">diaries</ref> gained recognition for their literary
					merit and were published posthumously in the twentieth century. <ref target="#tgenre_biography">Family biographies</ref> were another possible
					and popular form for women writers. Extending their work as family
					record-keepers, and drawing on family letters and diaries, many women writers
					wrote or completed the autobiographies and biographies of their fathers,
					husbands, or brothers, gaining status as published authors in their lifetimes as
					well as shoring up their private identities as devoted daughters, wives, and
					sisters. </p>
				<p><ref target="#pmotives_ascribed">Women writers created innovative forms that
						allowed them to write about women’s experience without breaching privacy:
							<ref target="#tgenre_biography">collective biographies of women</ref>,
						which typically feature several chapters, each devoted to a woman’s life,
						became increasingly popular throughout the nineteenth century. </ref>At the
					end of the century, women writers contributed to the development of the <ref target="#genre_biography">memoir</ref>: in these book-length works, the
					writer reports her recollections of events, famous people and times past, while
					keeping herself in the background. <note type="scholarNote"> Julie Rak notes
						that most contemporary literary critics see memoir as a record of a public
						life or a narrative that tells a person's life in terms of an event. Working
						on nineteenth century life writing, Mary Jean Corbett definition of memoir
						fits most closely with Rak’s first definition: women writers tended to write
						memoirs that focused on anecdotes of well-known figures and historical
						reportage, rather than themselves. Rak notes that memoir has long been seen
						as the “poor relative of autobiography discourse, a secondary form of life
						writing like diaries, confessions, letters or journals” but is now, in North
						America at least, becoming synonymous with autobiography following an
						explosion of popular memoirs in the early 2000s. See Julie Rak, “Are Memoirs
						Autobiography? A Consideration of Genre and Public Identity.” vol 37 no.
						3-4): 483–504. On nineteenth-century memoir, see Mary Jean Corbett,
						Representing Femininity: Middle-class Subjectivity in Victorian and
						Edwardian Women's Autobiographies (Oxford, Oxford UP, 1992), 12-13.
						</note><persName key="James Boswell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A88a01f90-9336-4c3b-85f5-032849180b89">Boswell</persName> may have written his <title level="m">Life of
						Johnson</title> (1791), but <persName key="Hester Piozzi" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ba14001b-f79e-45a9-aba8-19fc6bf99ae8">Hester Piozzi</persName> published her <title level="m">Anecdotes of the
						Late Samuel Johnson</title> (1786), an irreverent look at the great man’s
					domestic life and personal relations, five years earlier. Women writers often
					published such memoirs at the end of their lives, while letters and diaries were
					almost always published posthumously, often in the twentieth century either as
					local history or as part of feminist recovery projects. The primary subgenre of
						<ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographical</ref> writing that
					women did tend to publish in their lifetimes was <ref target="#tgenre_travelwriting">travel writing</ref>, a form we consider at
					length in chapter eight. While very few women writers wrote monograph-length
					biographies or autobiographies, biographical and autobiographical notices took
					many forms, from a <ref target="#tgenre_biography">biographical</ref> preface to
					a book of poems to recollections of a friend published as an article in a
					periodical, and these shorter forms were widely available to women writers. <ref target="#tgenreissue">When women writers wrote about their own lives, it was
						often in the form of a letter or manuscript for their children or
						grandchildren. These writings were often left incomplete; such was the case
						with <persName key="Mary Sewell" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:eac4b3e9-d527-41aa-885a-c8d181c47526">Mary Sewell</persName>’s autobiographical letter, which she began at
						age 82 to tell her grandchildren about their family, and worked on for five
						years but did not live to finish.</ref><note type="scholarNote">The letter
						eventually formed the first part of The Life and Letters of Mrs. Sewell
						(1889) </note>
					<ref target="#pmotives_ascribed">Women writers also incorporated <ref target="#tgenre_biography">biographical</ref> material into <ref target="#tgenre_novel">novels</ref> and <ref target="#tgenre_poetry">poetry</ref>, which maintained their privacy while allowing them to
						make literary use of their life experience. Women’s <ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">life writing</ref> in the nineteenth
						century, then, tended to grow out of and build upon women’s domestic duties
						as family archivists, and in the process, to present an interdependent,
						sociable, and familial version of the self. In this view, life writing is a
						relational, interdependent form.</ref></p>
				<p>This female version of <ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">life writing</ref>,
					which presents a relational self and grows out of the patriarchal conditions
					that stipulate that women’s lives were not worth writing, denying women access
					to education and archives, stands in contrast to the ego-centred masculine
					narratives that first emerged as objects of study at the end of the twentieth
						century.<note type="scholarNote">Eugene Stelzig, Romantic Autobiography in
						England (New York: Routledge, 2009), 5. </note> By and large,
					nineteenth-century women writers did not write monograph-length works focusing
					on their own individual development or that of other women; in other words,
					women did not write the kind of texts that interested scholars who first engaged
					with life writing. <ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">Life writing</ref> emerged
					as an object of literary studies in the 1980s, and the first narratives about
					life writing told the story of the spiritual and conversion narratives of great
					men, consolidating in the eighteenth century and flowering in the nineteenth
					century. This story of the development of <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiography</ref> often starts with <persName>Augustine</persName>,
					moving through <persName key="John Bunyan" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Acc074635-6861-4e7f-ab1c-86b4379104d8">John Bunyan</persName>, and then, in the nineteenth-century, focusing on
						<persName key="Thomas Carlyle" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:6064afb9-0af9-4f06-b20c-2551813c1fe9">Thomas Carlyle</persName>’s <title level="m">Sartor Resaurtus</title>,
						<persName key="John Henry Newman" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A226dfa8a-bc35-4c87-b14c-5f07d1c5d0d6">Cardinal Newman</persName>’s <title level="m">Apologia</title>,<persName key="John Stuart       Mill" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:29e9823d-ddaf-424e-9054-dc6ad024c8eb">John Stuart Mill</persName>’s <title level="m">Autobiography</title>, and
					finally <persName key="Edmund Gosse" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A018b4674-3a71-4bf2-9a11-eda834165b7f">Edmund Gosse</persName>’s <title level="m">Father and Son</title><note type="scholarNote">Trev Lynn Broughton, “Life Writing,” The Routledge
						Companion to Victorian Literature, Edited by Dennis Dennisoff and Talia
						Schaffer (New York: Routledge, 2020), 69.</note>. An alternate, but still
					masculine, genealogy of <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiography</ref>
					begins with <persName key="Jean-Jacques Rousseau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:03cdb094-674e-421c-ba64-e6bced4de54d">Rousseau’s</persName><title level="m">Confessions</title>, and sees acts of
					self-interpretation and mythmaking as essential to Romantic writers, as men
					writers including <persName>Thomas De Quincy</persName>, <persName key="William       Hazlitt" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:4f7c462c-99af-446d-a798-d9228a26263c">William Hazlitt</persName>, and <persName key="Charles Lamb" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A1ecbd1cb-3b27-4a1c-adb1-9777f1c49a04">Charles Lamb</persName> participate in ego-centric, personal mythmaking
					that is also a commodification of the self for the literary marketplace.<note type="scholarNote"> Stelzig, Romantic Autobiography, 3, quoting Michael
						Maschuch.</note></p>
				<p>Indeed, some scholars have argued that the Romantic period sees the
					autobiographization of literature,<note type="scholarNote">Stelzig, Romantic
						Autobiography, 3.</note> with many of the best known novels and poems of the
					century by both men and women, from <persName key="William Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aec7ae5ac-8fb2-4a08-b5fb-3cd485a339dd">Wordsworth</persName>’s <title level="m">The Prelude </title>and <persName key="Charles Dickens" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A294ea13f-024b-461c-a598-011e649b35fa">Dickens</persName>’s <title level="m">David Copperfield</title> to
						<persName key="Elizabeth Barrett Browning" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:7fa078f1-e346-4d74-a9c4-4e3e57e80cad">Elizabeth Barrett Browning</persName>’s <title ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando:5f5dc034-f7b8-4364-bc5c-f9c74bc6ac95">Aurora Leigh</title> and <persName key="Charlotte Brontë" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:a017e41e-6e1c-4c16-a575-82d25f7ec038">Charlotte Brontë</persName>’s <title ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:2801dd89-7791-4f8b-a0a7-57e115af1113">Jane Eyre</title>, containing a strong autobiographical element. In the
					nineteenth century, men writers tended to pattern their autobiographies on
					middle-class vocational narratives; like<title level="m">David
						Copperfield</title>, books including <title level="m">The Prelude</title>
					and <title level="m">Sartor Resartus</title> shored up men’s professional
					identity, following a narrative arc of apprenticeship resulting in a work of
					genius, and legitimising authorship as a worthy middle-class profession for
						men.<note type="scholarNote">Corbett, Representing Femininity, 11.</note>
					<ref target="#genreissue">With the exception of <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Harriet Martineau</persName>’s <title level="m">Autobiography,</title>
						women life writers did not tend to represent themselves as bourgeois
						subjects who found a vocation and ultimately success in writing. </ref><note type="scholarNote">Corbett, Representing Femininity, 12.</note> Instead,
					when women writers began to write autobiographies later in the nineteenth
					century, they blended their literary lives with their domestic lives.</p>
				<p>Beginning with an overview of the types of life writing that women wrote
					throughout the nineteenth century, this chapter traces the forms of women
					writers' <ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">life writing</ref> through the
					nineteenth century. The structure of this chapter, which progresses from <ref target="#tgenre_letter">letters</ref> and <ref target="#tgenre_diary">diaries</ref> to<ref target="#tgenre_biography"> biography, collective
						biography and memoir</ref>, ending with the <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiography</ref>, does in some ways
					replicate the masculine prestige of the genre. This is not to suggest that the
					forms of life writing that women took up were of less literary value or interest
					than the masculinized, monographic forms of biography and autobiography, but
					rather to highlight the conditions of generic development and the literary
					marketplace that women writers both worked within and challenged. <ref target="#tgenreissue">The relational emphasis of the “generic burden” of
						both the family biography and the memoir could diminish women writers’
						“capacity for self-presentation” as Linda Peterson argues of Sara Coleridge,
						whose autobiography focuses on her famous father’s circle.</ref><note type="scholarNote">Peterson, Traditions of Victorian Women’s Autobiography,
						27.</note> At the same time, our conception of an effective presentation of
					the self depends on nineteenth-century ideas of the individual, atomized self as
					superior to the relational self: women’s life writing challenges this notion by
					structuring life writing around relationships. While autobiography was
					consolidating as a genre over the course of the long nineteenth century, women
					writers entered the marketplace in greater numbers than ever before, and found
					new ways of engaging with and shaping this emerging form. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Life Writing by Numbers</head>
				<p><ref>After the <ref target="#tgenre_novel">novel</ref> and <ref target="#tgenre_poetry">poetry</ref>, <ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">life writing</ref> is the third most common genre that women writers
						born in the nineteenth century produced. This is perhaps because women
						writers drew from their lives in many genres, and it was perhaps more
						acceptable to draw on their life experience indirectly in the form of <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographical</ref>
						<ref target="#tgenre_fiction">fiction</ref> or poetry, rather than to use it
						directly in an autobiography. There were also many opportunities for women
						to write about lives in shorter forms, including <ref target="#tgenre_prefatorypiece">prefaces</ref>, <ref target="#tgenre_sketch">sketches</ref>, and <ref target="#tgenre_periodical">periodical pieces</ref>.</ref> When women
					wrote about their lives for publication in their lifetime, they often used
					material from their lives to inform their fiction rather than writing an
					autobiography openly and directly centering themselves and their own
					experiences. Fictionalizing elements of their lives allowed women writers, to
					some extent, to circumvent the problem of the unfeminine exposure of their
					personal life. <ref>In <title level="m">The Valley of a Hundred Fires
						</title>(1860), an industrial novel, <persName key="Julia Stretton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae0c99839-701f-4667-ad9f-16e1af624d4f">Julia Stretton</persName> (1812-1878) models Mr and Mrs Leslie, a
						clergyman and his wife who settle in Wales to improve the lot of the working
						people who toil in filthy factories, after her parents. The <ref target="#tgenre_novel">novel</ref> is also a family drama that,
						unusually in a form that tends to center on the individual protagonist,
						follows the upbringing and courtship of twelve children. (<persName key="Julia Stretton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae0c99839-701f-4667-ad9f-16e1af624d4f">Stretton</persName> was the eldest of 15 children herself.) The novel
						can be read as a celebration of <persName key="Julia Stretton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae0c99839-701f-4667-ad9f-16e1af624d4f">Stretton</persName>’s mother.</ref>
					<ref target="tgenreissue"><persName key="Charlotte Riddell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ab5429148-5662-456f-9060-dd9354e6c090">Charlotte Riddell</persName>’s (1832-1906) <title level="m">A Struggle
							for Fame </title> (1883), has been read as semi-autobiographical in its
						presentation of a young woman trying to make her way in the public,
						money-earning world of the writer.</ref>
					<ref target="#tgenreissue"><persName key="Mary Hay" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A2a08864a-31e0-4317-b3cf-19eb5be969c9">Mary Hay</persName>s’s <title level="m">Memoirs of Emma
							Courtney</title>, <persName key="Mary Wollstonecraft" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:25504fac-570f-4fb6-bee5-73314bed90ae">Mary Wollstonecraft</persName>’s <title level="m">Maria, or the Wrongs
							of Woman</title> are among well-known fictionalizations of their
						authors’ lives.</ref> The practice of fictionalizing one’s life experience
					may seem unremarkable from a contemporary perspective. <ref target="#prelationswithpublisher">But looking at nineteenth-century women’s
							<ref target="#tgenre_lifeWriting">life writing</ref> as a whole,
						fictionalizing autobiographical material emerges as a significant strategy
						in a literary marketplace that all but barred women from publishing
						book-length material about their lives.</ref></p>
				<p>
					<figure>
						<graphic url="https://github.com/SusanBrown/Orlando_DToC/blob/main/DToC-7-LivesofWriting-Image1.png"/>
					</figure>
				</p>
				<p>A tree map showing works by women published in the nineteenth century which are
					tagged as autobiographical writing, as well as what other genres they are tagged
					in, illustrates the patterns that shaped women’s autobiographical writing in the
					nineteenth century. Published <ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiographical</ref> material was almost as likely to show up in a <ref target="#tgenre_novel">novel</ref> (130 titles) as it was in a <ref target="#tgenre_diary">diary</ref> (138 titles); though the diaries were
					likely to be published decades after the author’s death while novels were
					typically published in their lifetimes. The most dominant monographic form is
						<ref target="#tgenre_travelwriting">travel writing,</ref> which we explore
					at length in another chapter (63 titles). <ref target="#tgenreissue">Autobiographical texts are quite often tagged as “<ref target="#tgenre_prefatorypiece">prefatory piece</ref>,” “<ref target="#tgenre_essay">essay</ref>,” “<ref target="#tgenre_sketch">sketch</ref>,” and “<ref target="#tgenre_introduction">introduction</ref>.”</ref>
				</p>
				<p>
					<figure>
						<graphic url="https://github.com/SusanBrown/Orlando_DToC/blob/main/DToC-7-LivesinWriting-Image2.png"/>
					</figure>
				</p>
				<p>A bar chart gives an idea of the autobiographization of literature over time,
					with each bar showing the number of titles tagged “<ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiography</ref>” published in that
					decade. Like the tree map at the beginning of this chapter, the bar chart shows
					all texts marked with the tag “<ref target="#tgenre_autobiography">autobiography</ref>”, ranging from autobiographical <ref>novels</ref> and
						<ref>poems</ref> to <ref>essays</ref> and <ref>diaries</ref>. In the 1790s,
					autobiographical texts spike, perhaps in response to the momentous events of the
					decade (19 titles), and then they double again in the 1850s (39 titles). But
					overall, autobiographical literature belongs to the twentieth century, doubling
					once more in the 1930s (84) and staying roughly in that range for the remainder
					of the twentieth century despite the relatively few entries for women writers in
					those decades. It was becoming more possible, this bar chart seems to suggest,
					for women in the twentieth century to write about themselves. </p>
				<p>
					<figure>
						<graphic url="https://github.com/SusanBrown/Orlando_DToC/blob/main/DToC-7-LivesinWriting-Image3.jpg"/>
					</figure>
				</p>
			</div>
			
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Letters and Diaries</head>
				<p>For most middle and upper class women in the nineteenth century, writing letters
					was part and parcel of managing domestic ife. Letters are perhaps the only form
					of writing in the nineteenth century that women were not only authorised to
					write, but had a duty to keep up with on behalf of their families. Indeed,
					letters and diaries, which can be read as part of the feminine occupation of
					family recordkeeper, are among the earliest surviving pieces of women’s writing.
					All literate women would have written letters to keep up with the business of
					daily life, and even those who did not read or write would have been likely to
					dictate letters (or later in the century, a telegraph) at some point in their
					lives. Many women writers also kept a diary. Of women born between 1780 and 1900
					with a profile in Orlando, around 17% ultimately published a title that was also
					tagged as a diary (this percentage includes both diaries and diaries
					incorporated into other forms, like novels); many more women writers likely kept
					a diary that was never published <note type="scholarNote"> This percentage also
						includes other genres, such as novels, that include fictionalized diary
						entries, such as Dinah Craik’s A Life for a Life.</note>. Many women writers
					kept a diary from a young age: <persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Grace Aguilar</persName> kept her diary (now lost) from age 7 onward, and
						<persName key="Beatrix Potter" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af71d06c2-e704-4213-9b0c-d2ce4fd059b4">Beatrix Potter</persName> wrote her diary in code from age 15 for nearly
					sixteen years. <persName key="Anna Margaetta Larpent" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa7ba1041-2d56-47bf-ab87-399558ea69a4">Anna Magaretta Larpent</persName> kept a diary from age 15 for fifty years
					spanning the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, and including
					important commentary on the theatre (her husband was Licenser of Plays). Letters
					and diaries, which are generally meant to be private or for the eyes of a few
					select correspondents, and often carried out family business, keeping in touch
					with faraway relatives or inviting a friend to tea, were not controversial for
					women to write. As any scholar who has spent significant time in the archives
					can attest, most of these diaries and even many of the letters are likely to be
					about the business of quotidian life. Nineteenth-century diaries typically
					briefly record the memoranda of everyday life with little explanatory or
					emotional content. Many letters will advise on daily business like train times.
					Except in the case of very famous authors, like <persName key="Elizabeth Barrett Browning" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A7fa078f1-e346-4d74-a9c4-4e3e57e80cad">Elizabeth Barrett</persName> and <persName key="Robert Browning" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6315e747-c757-448c-be99-8f4a8ca854ad">Robert Browning</persName>, these diaries and letters are unlikely to be
					published in full. And yet, a larger case can be made for the importance of
					seemingly personal diaries and letters in women’s literary culture.
					Nineteenth-century women’s letters and diaries have not only received posthumous
					recognition for their literary value in and of themselves, but they were also
					pivotal in shaping the course of biography, autobiography, and fiction. </p>
				<p> Surviving private letters and diaries represent a network of correspondents and
					can help us uncover the sociability that helped women writers into their
					careers. Letters and diaries also informed the development of literary genres
					and modes of publication. Writing about the eighteenth century,
						<persName>Rachael Scarborough King</persName> argues that the letter
					functions as a “bridge genre” between old and new media in an age of the
					proliferation of print: “Newspapers relied on letters from “foreign
					correspondents” for content; periodicals initiated interactions with readers in
					the form of letters to the editor; biographical “lives” used letters as
					documentary evidence; and novels deployed them to transmit unfolding
					narratives.” <note type="scholarNote">Rachael Scarborough King, <title level="m">Writing to the World: Letters and the Origins of Modern Print
							Genres</title> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 2018),
						4.</note> By the nineteenth century, the epistolary novel–best known in
						<persName key="Samuel Richardson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ab691b8e8-4330-4de1-9a92-1dcb4880fbee">Richardson</persName>’s <title level="m">Pamela</title> and <title level="m">Clarissa</title>–had fallen out of vogue, but fictitious
					correspondence still made its way into most novels, and the letter continued to
					be a firmly entrenched part of newspaper and periodical culture and biography.
					Past the heyday of <persName key="Samuel Richardson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ab691b8e8-4330-4de1-9a92-1dcb4880fbee">Richardson</persName>, women writers continued to publish epistolary
					novels, from <persName>Eliza Parson’</persName>s <title level="m">The History of
						Miss Meredith </title> (1790) to <persName>Elizabeth von Armin</persName>’s
						<title level="m">Fräulein Schmidt</title> and <title level="m">Mr.
						Anstruther</title> (1907). <persName key="Anne Brontë" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A2ec044e6-30f3-4fba-970e-676ec81c79fc">Anne Brontë</persName>’s <title level="m">The Tenant of Wildfell
						Hall</title> (1848) takes the form of an epistolary exchange between
					gentleman farmer Gilbert Marham and his brother-in-law about Mrs. Graham, the
					tenant of the title, whose diaries are also embedded in the narrative. As
					Catherine Delafield notes, nineteenth-century women’s letters were “authorised
					as a domestic duty” but for women writers, there was always the worrying
					possibility that these personal artefacts would reach the public in a biography.
						<note type="scholarNote">Catherine Delafield, <title level="m">Women’s
							Letters as Life Writing, 1840–1885 </title>(New York: Routledge, 2020),
						1.</note> The letters and diaries of almost all nineteenth-century women
					writers, including those who became famous posthumously as <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Dorothy Wordsworth </persName>did for her journals and <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Jane Welsh Carlyle</persName> did for her letters, were not published until
					well after their deaths. </p>
				<p>Posthumous publication allowed these nineteenth-century letter writers and
					diarists to maintain womanly privacy during their lifetime; when nineteenth
					century women wrote autobiographical reminiscences, they tended to have a
					private family audience in mind, writing letters for their children and
					grandchildren. Throughout the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, letters and
					diaries became increasingly accepted as a genuine literary genre, alongside an
					increasing recognition of the value of women’s private literary productions. In
					other words, it was more acceptable for a woman’s diaries and letters to be
					published after her death, by someone else; several eighteenth-century women
					writers entered print this way in the nineteenth and even twentieth centuries.
						<persName key="Melesina Trench" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A39b018aa-cea2-494e-92e3-1984f49bde36">Melesina Trench</persName> (1768-1827), an Anglo-Irish poet, stands in some
					ways as a typical upper-class amateur writer, whose output was mainly diaries
					and letters, published after her death by one of her sons, <persName key="Richard Chenevix Trench" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A4cb9ba2c-e6c9-4d10-982b-bce4668a78fd">Richard Chenevix Trench</persName>. In his preface to <title level="m">The
						Remains of the Late Mrs. Richard Trench </title>(1861), which included
					twenty pages of reminiscences followed by a mix of letters, journals, poems
					prose sketches, and reprinted minor publications, <persName key="Melesina Trench" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A39b018aa-cea2-494e-92e3-1984f49bde36">Trench</persName>’s son claimed “it is only reluctantly . . . that I at all
					disturb this sacred obscurity”. And yet, he went on to publish her life writing,
					which included personal records of mourning for those of her children who died
					in infancy and childhood, as well as her thoughts on the current events and
					literature of the turn of the century. It was likely her gossip about
						<persName>Nelson</persName>, and his mistress <persName>Lady
						Hamilton</persName>, whom she had met in Europe, that was responsible for
					the first printing selling out almost immediately. <persName key="Ann Taylor Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af3b0eb7a-8c38-4d3f-a4b7-6c5138f21ea8">Ann Taylor Gilbert</persName>’s son <persName>Josiah</persName> also edited
					and posthumously published her<title level="m"> Autobiography and Other
						Memorials</title> (1874), which <persName key="Ann Taylor Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af3b0eb7a-8c38-4d3f-a4b7-6c5138f21ea8">Gilbert</persName>, like many women writers, began writing for her children
					and left incomplete on her death.</p>
				<p>In the last third of the twentieth century, some nineteenth-century women’s life
					writing was published as part of a conscious effort to diversify our
					understanding of the nineteenth century; as Felicity Nussbaum argues, these
					diaries and journals allow us to hear alternate voices that destabilize the
					bourgeois, gendered self. The letters of <persName key="Margaret Catchpole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aba8987ae-6bd1-43af-90f0-556be532356b">Margaret Catchpole</persName> (1762-1819), an illegitimate servant who
					gained notoriety when she abetted a theft and was subsequently transported as a
					felon to New South Wales, Australia, were published in the late 1970s through
					the 1990s. (In the nineteenth century, her life was also fictionalized in
					Richard Cobbold’s novel <title level="m">The History of Margaret Catchpole, a
						Suffolk Girl</title> (1845)). This pattern of posthumous publication
					continues with writers who are now celebrated for their journals and letters;
					which, for the most part, were published throughout the twentieth century.
					Nineteenth-century women’s life writing published for the first time early in
					the twentieth century tended to come to print as part and parcel of the work of
					well-known men, as is the case of <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Dorothy Wordsworth</persName>’s journals or <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Jane Carlyle</persName>’s letters, or as part of work on local history, as
					is the case in <persName>Anne Lister</persName>’s local journals.</p>
				<p>Perhaps the most celebrated journals published after their author’s death are
					those of <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Dorothy Wordsworth</persName> (1771-1855). While her brother, William, was
					one of the most famous poets of the nineteenth century, <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Dorothy Wordsworth</persName>’s private journals were not published until
					1897, more than forty years after her death, when a selection first appeared.
					The style of <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Wordsworth</persName>’s journals is deceptively simple, as she writes an
					entry for each day in a tabulated style. Her subjects range from nature to
					people, as she details the precise circumstances and personal pleasures of the
					rural poor and vagrants. As spring comes to Alfoxden, her home with her brother
					William, in 1798 she writes: “The green paths down the hill-sides are channels
					for streams. The young wheat is streaked by silver lines of water running
					between the ridges… Upon the highest ridge of that round hill covered with
					planted oaks, the shafts of the trees show in the light like the columns of a
					ruin.” Scholars have established that her Grasmere journals, containing original
					accounts of daffodils dancing on the lake shore and of an old-leech gatherer,
					are the source of William’s poems <title level="m">“I wandered Lonely as a
						Cloud”</title> and <title level="m">“Resolution and Independence”,</title>
					down to some of the exact phrasing. Like her brother, <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Wordsworth</persName> finds deep emotions in seemingly insignificant
					incidents. In 1802, she writes: “I lay upon the steep of Loughrigg, my heart
					dissolved in what I saw, when I was not startled but re-called from my reverie
					by a noise as of a child paddling without shoes. I looked up and saw a lamb
					close to me. It approached nearer and nearer, as if to examine me, and stood a
					long time. I did not move. At last it ran past me . . .” Commenting on a local
					acquaintance, she writes, “I saw Jane Ashburner driving the cow along the high
					road from the well where she had been watering it—she had a stick in her hand
					and came tripping along in the jig-step, as if she were dancing. Her presence
					was bold and graceful, her cheeks flushed with health, and her countenance was
					free and gay.” </p>
				<p>In a reversal of the many women writers who published their husbands’ lives and
					letters after their deaths, it was <persName key="Thomas Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6064afb9-0af9-4f06-b20c-2551813c1fe9">Thomas Carlyle</persName> who first began to assemble, transcribe and
					annotate his wife <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Jane Carlyle</persName>’s letters, which he declared to be “an electric
					shower of all-illuminating brilliancy,” after her death. <persName key="Thomas Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6064afb9-0af9-4f06-b20c-2551813c1fe9">Thomas Carlyle</persName> was unsure of whether to publish his wife’s
					letters, and the decision to publish fell to his literary executor, <persName key="James Anthony Froude" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A398f05ce-a5c3-4a92-950a-9cb2abaa983b">James Anthony Froude.</persName> The letters were published to controversy
					in 1883, as some felt that <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Jane Carlyle</persName>’s descriptions of her husband’s neglect and their
					marital strife should have remained private. And yet, <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Carlyle’s</persName> highly autobiographical and self-reflexive letters
					have received praise. Written in a conversational style, with her famous sense
					of wit and irony, they typically feature comic vignettes of her domestic life in
					Chelsea. <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Carlyle's</persName> talent for capturing dialogue and her pride in her
					Scotch ability to manage a household economically are captured in a letter to
					her mother-in-law in 1834: I told Mrs [Leigh] Hunt, one day, I had been very
					busy painting. What? she asked, is it a portrait? Oh! no, I told her; something
					of more importance—a large wardrobe. She could not imagine, she said, how I
					could have patience for such things? And so, having no patience for them
					herself, what is the result? She is every other day reduced to borrow my
					tumblers, my teacups…” Carlyle is self-reflexive about the practice of letter
					writing; her letters often refer to the practice of writing letters. She was
					acutely aware of the dynamics of the epistolary project and had high standards.
					In 1860, she reprimanded her husband for his lack of affect in a recent letter:
					“Oh my dear! If all about feelings be bad in a letter, all about scenery and no
					feelings is a deal worse! Such a letter as that I received from you, yesterday,
					after much half-anxious, half-angry waiting for, will read charmingly in your
					biography! and may be quoted in Murray's Guide Book; but for me, as one solitary
					individual, I was not charmed with it at all!” Readers have, however, been
					charmed by <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b">Jane Carlyle</persName>’s letters, which reached a near-canonical status in
					the twentieth century, and were included in school readers. </p>
				<p>While <persName key="Doroth Wordsworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac5060e0a-3967-4f91-b6fc-20552a30df40">Wordsworth</persName> and <persName key="Jane Welsh Carlyle" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6b535565-ffb3-4ed2-b883-e12733d8a95b"> Carlyle</persName> were educated women born into the middle and
					upper-middle class rungs of society (and, not incidentally, related to some of
					the most well-known men writers of the nineteenth century), <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Hannah Cullwick</persName>’s (1833-1909) diaries, written between 1854 and
					1873, and published for the first time in the 1980s, offer a rare glimpse into
					the harsh material conditions of maids of all work. <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName> was unknown in her lifetime; her diaries came to light
					when barrister <persName key="Arthur Munby" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6649b302-edf9-4cb3-a6fa-f64d575c890b">Arthur Munby</persName>’s will revealed his secret cross-class marriage
					with his maid of all work in 1910. The revelation of the marriage of a gentleman
					to his maid caused a furore in the newspapers. Her diary entries, which she
					first wrote at <persName key="Arthur Munby" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6649b302-edf9-4cb3-a6fa-f64d575c890b">Munby</persName>’s behest and later continued, function as a form of
					self-expression and a means of influencing her relationship with <persName key="Arthur Munsby" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6649b302-edf9-4cb3-a6fa-f64d575c890b">Munby</persName>, as her editor Liz Stanley has argued. The diaries
					catalogue the repetitious minutiae of her labour day after day, mainly without
					emotion or analysis. The diaries also had an erotic function. <persName key="Arthur Munby" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6649b302-edf9-4cb3-a6fa-f64d575c890b">Munby</persName> eroticized <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName>’s dirty work, much of which, like blacking boots or a
					grate, literally blackened her as well. <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName> called Munby “Massa”, based on how the pair thought
					enslaved people in the Southern U.S. pronounced “master.” Much of her diary
					writing functioned as a fetish for <persName key="Arthur Munby" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6649b302-edf9-4cb3-a6fa-f64d575c890b">Munby</persName>, including a particularly erotic representation of herself
					sweeping a chimney: </p>
				<p>I come down, &amp; lay on the hearth in the soot a minute or two thinking, &amp;
					I wish'd rather that Massa could see me. I black'd my face over then got the
					looking glass look'd at myself &amp; I was certainly a fright &amp; hideous all
					over, at least I should o' seem'd so to anybody but Massa. I set on &amp; wash'd
					myself after, &amp; I'd hard work to get the black off &amp; was obliged to
					leave my shoulders for Massa to finish. </p>
				<p>In this sexual dynamic, <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName> further subordinates herself by invoking colonialism
					and slavery through what Cora Kaplan has argued are links in “a chain of
					colonial associations—feminized, blackened and impoverished” with “each
					denigrating construction implying and invoking the others.” And yet, <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName> also actively staged herself. At the studio of one
					photographer, she arrived dirty, with additional lead for blacking herself up
					further, telling him: “I want to be done thoroughly black like I am sometimes at
					work.” Surviving photographs show <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName> staging herself in a range of class, racial and
					gendered identities: as a lady, a naked enslaved person, and a man. Anne
					McClintock argues that <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName>’s manipulation of the signs of female labour and the
					iconography of empire in these representations of herself was “a profound
					engagement with the social edicts that brutally circumscribed her life.” The
					diaries were published for the first time in 1984, 75 years after <persName key="Hannah Cullwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9eb85abc-31e8-42d2-88a1-297a7658ebff">Cullwick</persName>’s death.</p>
				<p>The diary of the lesbian couple <persName key="Katharine Harris Bradley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adeb7aad8-886e-4c8d-94cd-d8c5a712d144">Katharine Harris Bradley</persName> and <persName key="Edith Cooper">Edith
						Cooper</persName>, who were also aunt and niece and best known for the
					poetry they co-authored and published together under the pen name of Michael
					Field, pushed the boundaries of form. Instead of recording the private musings
					of a single individual, the vast journal kept by the couple from 1888 to 1914,
					which was not originally intended for publication, soon became a collaborative
					text produced with some intention of publication. The diaries, which contain
					both <persName key="Katharine Harris Bradley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adeb7aad8-886e-4c8d-94cd-d8c5a712d144">Bradley</persName> and Harris’s impressions of travel, art, religion,
					death, and lovae, also record their encounters with literary celebrities
					including <persName key="Robert Browning" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6315e747-c757-448c-be99-8f4a8ca854ad">Robert Browning</persName>, <persName key="George Meredith" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5b26aa77-7cfa-4573-84b6-0f3f5d53e43b">George Meredith</persName>, <persName key="John Ruskin" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac8855e0f-6852-4da4-afb5-f0374ec1adde">John Ruskin</persName>, <persName key="Walter Pater" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A545b772a-c106-4657-8e48-19416441512d">Walter Pater</persName>, <persName key="Anna Swanwick" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8a16fac0-1114-40bf-8077-e726e129442c">Anna Swanwick</persName>, <persName key="Oscar Wilde" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aee8e39a1-5690-438f-b572-42bde3d38c73">Oscar Wilde</persName>, and <persName key="Vernon Lee" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A437ce0fc-2437-4f8b-9927-18d9ed5dfcb1">Vernon Lee</persName>. The diary further pushes form by including letters
					from some of these contemporaries. The original twenty-six vellum-bound folios
					are now held in the <placeName key="British Library" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q23308">British library</placeName>, but
					before their death <persName key="Michael Field" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A1acf06dc-5b6d-4732-a0b8-5a0f6b97c6ea">Michael Field</persName> entrusted the publisher <persName key="T. Sturge Moore" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A58a99cc6-446c-4e3f-9c3c-5e7da6955b93">T. Sturge Moore</persName> to read and publish parts of the diary and
					letters. Bowdlerised extracts of the diary appeared in 1933, twenty years after
					the couple both died from cancer within ten months of each other, <persName key="Edith Cooper">Cooper</persName> died in December 1913, followed by
						<persName key="Katharine Harris Bradley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adeb7aad8-886e-4c8d-94cd-d8c5a712d144">Bradley</persName> in September 1914. A consortium of scholars housed at
						<placeName key="Dartmouth College" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q49116">Dartmouth</placeName> and
						<placeName key="Kings College London" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q245247">King’s College
						London</placeName> is in the midst of transcribing, encoding, and digitising
					the full twenty-six volumes. </p>
				<p>Sexual content in nineteenth century women’s diaries was typically kept hidden
					until the rise of gender and sexuality studies in the last third of the
					twentieth century. Women’s diaries, including sexual content, could, however, be
					published against their will if they came up as evidence in court; the
					Matrimonial Causes Act of 1857 made divorce a civil matter rather than an
					ecclesiastical matter, and ultimately allowed more couples to divorce.
					Newspapers printed reports of divorce trials, ostensibly to dissuade people from
					divorcing, but in reality the reports made salacious reading, often at the
					expense of women. Excerpts of <persName key="Isabella Hamilton Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa4378d42-49c2-4373-83c3-0a86cd392d76">Isabella Hamilton Robinson</persName>’s (1813-1887) diaries appeared in the
					papers as part of her sensational divorce trial. The diary, kept from 1849 to
					1855, detailed her frustrating home life and uninspired marriage, which stood in
					contrast to her romantic longings and ultimate affair with <persName key="Edward Lane" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0d33207d-52b7-4c52-a2b5-1657b4169d45">Edward Lane</persName>, a younger, married doctor. Scholars have linked
						<persName key="Isabella Hamilton Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa4378d42-49c2-4373-83c3-0a86cd392d76">Robinson’s</persName> diary, excerpted against her will in newspapers, to
					the development of sensation fiction, which revolves around the secrets and
					scandals of the middle class home. Moralists objected, but readers were
					enthralled to discover that, as Kate Summerscale writes in <title level="m">Mrs
						Robinson’s Disgrace</title> (2012), <persName key="Isabella Hamilton Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa4378d42-49c2-4373-83c3-0a86cd392d76">Isabella Robinson's</persName> diary showed that a middle-class
					Englishwoman could assault her own decency in prose. <persName key="Isabella Hamilton Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa4378d42-49c2-4373-83c3-0a86cd392d76">Robinson’s</persName> diary was published in her lifetime, but it was
					against her will. One woman who purposefully exposed the workings of her
					marriage was <persName key="Rosina Bulwer Lytton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A1a82015b-d849-474c-937e-c247c7c37506">Rosina Bulwer Lytton</persName>, who wrote and published <title level="m">A
						Blighted Life</title> (1880), which takes the form of a letter, to take
					revenge on her husband <persName key="Edward Bulwer Lytton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A90b9aa84-2b18-4842-b3b8-d8e214e38154">Edward Bulwer Lytton</persName>, who had her wrongfully confined to an
					asylum after she spoke against his political career. </p>
				<p>One of the only nineteenth-century women who willingly published her diaries, or
					at least, heavily-edited excerpts from them, in her lifetime was <persName key="Queen Victoria" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A68336d67-737e-4d46-9625-140373914ce8">Queen Victoria.</persName> Her status as a national figure authorised the
					anomalous publication of <title level="m">Leaves from the Journal of Our Life in
						the Highlands</title> (1868), and <title level="m">More Leaves from the
						Journal of Our Life in the Highlands</title> (1884). Yet the choice of the
					private family diary for <persName key="Queen Victoria" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A68336d67-737e-4d46-9625-140373914ce8">Queen Victoria’s</persName> publication served to shore up her status as a
					private wife and mother as well as mother to the nation. The journals chronicle
					her personal life, pastimes and travels in <placeName>England</placeName>,
						<placeName>Ireland</placeName>, and <placeName>Scotland</placeName> between
					1848 and 1861. Anecdotes around the publication of her diaries emphasise the
					private, unprofessional nature of the <persName key="Queen Victoria" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A68336d67-737e-4d46-9625-140373914ce8">Queen’s</persName> writing. <persName key="Arthur Helps" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A84caed05-8c3b-405f-9394-b0130691ea5a">Arthur Helps,</persName> a Privy Council clerk, suggested publication to
					the <persName key="Queen Victoria" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A68336d67-737e-4d46-9625-140373914ce8">Queen</persName> when she showed him extracts focusing on her life at
					Balmoral; the <persName key="Queen Victoria" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A68336d67-737e-4d46-9625-140373914ce8">Queen</persName> at first demurred, arguing that “she had no skill whatever
					in authorship; that these were, for the most part, mere homely accounts of
					excursions near home; and that she felt extremely reluctant to publish any thing
					written by herself.” <persName key="Arthur Helps" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A84caed05-8c3b-405f-9394-b0130691ea5a">Helps</persName> prevailed, and the resulting book paints a picture of her
					domestic bliss with <persName key="Prince Albert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A2950764d-3a43-4406-8ce0-11c603182d0b">Prince Albert</persName> and their children, an appreciation of beautiful
					landscapes, and lists of people and events; <persName key="Arthur Helps" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A84caed05-8c3b-405f-9394-b0130691ea5a">Helps</persName> excised her commentary on political and governmental
					matters. Although the publication during her lifetime was unusual for a woman
					writer, her diary, the public version of her diary, with political commentary
					excised, and focusing instead on “homely accounts” of her families’ excursions
					in the Highlands, and Victoria’s protests that she has “no skill” as a writer,
					were congruent with ideals of women’s role in the domestic sphere. As such, the
					diaries served to reconcile her identities as mother in private life and mother
					of the nation.</p>
				<p/>
			</div>
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Biography</head>
				<p>If letters and diaries were congruent with women’s domestic duties, the family
					biography was in some ways a natural extension of these private, domestic forms.
					The standard nineteenth-century biography, also tellingly called
					lives-and-letters, consists mainly of letters stitched together with a scant
					narrative. Before the final decade of the nineteenth century, women writers
					tended to write family biography, focusing on the lives and letters of their
					husbands and fathers, and typically ending with the death of their male relative
					or in an ellipses. In the Orlando textbase, women were about ten times as likely
					to publish biographical material about their fathers, husbands, or brothers (in
					that order of popularity) during the long nineteenth century as they were to
					publish about a mother or a sister. Writing about men may have been legitimating
					for women writers. This strand of biography has received little scholarly
					attention, likely because it sits uneasily with feminist critics, who
					understandably prefer to focus on women writing about women. Meanwhile, scholars
					focused on men writers may use women writers’ biographies of their fathers and
					husbands as a source of more or less factual information, but are less likely to
					be interested in these biographies as works of literature. Yet, the
					preponderance of women writing about their fathers and husbands suggests that
					such writings, which ranged in length from magazine articles to prefaces to full
					length biographies, happily combined filial piety with an authorization to
					publish. In other words, the dutiful daughter or wife writing about her husband
					or father would have had every reason to break the privacy of the domestic
					sphere and publish her reminiscences, while adhering to middle-class standards
					of femininity. Writing about their men relatives, or sometimes, their family
					history with a focus on male relatives, which relied on and wove together
					letters, diaries and other family records, was in many ways a natural extension
					of women’s work in maintaining family correspondence and diaries, and acting as
					family archivists. Titles such as <persName key="Sarah Tytler" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A17e19565-ad13-4f18-9ff1-c0386faafaad">Sarah Tytler’s</persName> (Henrietta Keddie) final publication, <title level="m">Three Generations: The Story of a Middle-Class Scottish
						Family</title> (1911), where the emphasis is on anecdotes of literary life
					rather than herself and her siblings, allowed their authors to highlight the
					family and domestic life while writing autobiographically. (Unusually, Keddie
					focuses on her mother’s family rather than her father’s.)</p>
				<p>One reason that so many women writers wrote memoirs of their fathers and husbands
					may be that life writing can be quite short, including not only full-length
					lives and letters, but also prefaces and articles in periodicals. Women writers
					wrote biographies and memoirs of their male relatives at all lengths, from a
					preface with a memoir to an edition of their poetry, as <persName key="Adelaide OKeeffe" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A1ca8ebcd-05ea-46a8-9053-dc5edef82aab">Adelaide O’Keeffe</persName> did in <title level="m">O'Keeffe's Legacy to
						his Daughter, Being the Poetical Works of the Late John O'Keeffe, Esq., the
						Dramatic Author </title>(1834), to <persName key="Helen Craik" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac8129437-bb58-4ece-8325-9e966f1f19b7">Helen Craik’s</persName> two letters containing a memoir of her father
						<persName key="William Craik" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af3cf6427-5bab-4fda-991d-2ad363abd905">William Craik</persName> of <placeName>Arbigland Hall,
						Dumfriesshire</placeName>, in the <title level="m">Farmer’s Magazine
					</title>(1811). Similarly, <persName key="Anna Laetitia Barbauld" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A43505af0-5a9b-4d80-ae71-c09ca4d84579">Anna Laetitia Barbauld</persName> published her “Memoir of the Rev. R.
					Barbauld” in the <title level="m">Monthly Repository</title> in 1808. Writing
					about the lives of husbands and fathers could form part of the corpus of a woman
					writer at any stage of her career. A biography of her father the Rev. <persName key="Alexander Scott" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0c3c674f-82ea-4354-ad9a-22a6d022d601">Alexander Scott</persName>, a chaplain in the British navy, titled <title level="m">Recollections</title> (1842), was the first work that the
					children’s author <persName key="Margaret Gatty" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abd2bfb3a-387f-4a9f-938d-328af4e39b68">Margaret Gatty</persName> published in her early thirties. She compiled it
					with her husband and included extracts from their father’s diary. <title level="m">Memoirs of Doctor Burney</title> (1832), a lovingly laboured and
					highly deferential work was the last thing that <persName key="Frances Burney" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aed1c2d59-1fbd-4843-bca8-ec1dec605264">Frances Burney</persName> ever published. She omitted any hint of scandal
					or even of low associations of any member of the Burney family. And yet, the
					work was not well-received. <persName key="Joanna Baillie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A697d2560-04b6-43f4-baa0-ef562e5847ff">Joanna Baillie</persName> and her sister, who knew many of the people
					depicted in the memoirs, enjoyed them immensely, but <persName key="John Wilson Croker" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A43efc598-d0d9-437b-b741-c23245ec5cc5">J. W. Croker</persName> savaged them in the Quarterly review, attacking
					Burney’s character as well as her work. Daughterly devotion was not always
					enough, then, to win women writers praise.</p>
				<p>Women writers took it upon themselves to complete the autobiographies and last
					works of their husbands and fathers, as <persName key="Catherine Hutton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8d28bef9-3714-4ae4-9c6a-20dabcaa7b82">Catherine Hutton</persName> did when she edited, completed and saw through
					to publication an autobiography of her father, <title level="m">The Life of
						William Hutton</title> (1816), in the year after his death. Hutton’s father,
					who made his fortune as a publisher and bookseller, was a
						<placeName>Birmingham</placeName> celebrity and local historian known for
					his <title level="m">History of Birmingham </title>(1781). The Huttons were a
					Dissenting family of the English midland manufacturing class; <persName key="William Hutton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A92c85066-2bb4-4017-bb85-0e8ffb157840">William Hutton’s</persName> own father had made money in wool, but had
					subsequently gone bankrupt. Of her father’s life, she wrote, “I look upon my
					father's history to be the most complete picture of human life . . . that ever
					was drawn by man.” <title level="m">The Life of William Hutton</title> went
					through many editions, with <persName key="William Hutton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A92c85066-2bb4-4017-bb85-0e8ffb157840">Hutton</persName> adding to it in 1817 and 1841. Jane Loudon, best known in
					her own right as the author of <title level="m">The Mummy! A Tale of the
						Twenty-Second Century </title>(1827) and a literary hostess as well as a
					writer about gardening, saw to it that her husband’s <title level="m">Self-Instruction for Young Gardeners, Foresters, Bailiffs, Land-Stewards,
						and Farmers by John Claudius Loudon </title>(1845), to which she added an
					account of his life was published posthumously. </p>
				<p>While many nineteenth-century white women throughout <placeName>Great
						Britain</placeName> memorialised their male relatives, <persName key="Anne Hart Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A162ae917-e7ab-4d72-a60d-c27cbdbcadb7">Anne Hart Gilbert</persName> (1768-1834), the eldest daughter of a
					mixed-race free family in Antigua, shows that this trope also operated in the
					colonial context. At least two of the daughters of this large Methodist family,
						<persName key="Anne Hart Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A162ae917-e7ab-4d72-a60d-c27cbdbcadb7">Anne</persName> and her sister Elizabeth, both taught Sunday school and
					wrote about religion. Anne married <persName key="John Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abe6d6146-3a0d-42fb-8808-e017d0763beb">John Gilbert,</persName> a baker and accountant of a white English settler
					family in the Caribbean, despite the prejudice they faced as a mixed race
					couple, which included being refused a marriage licence and having the door of
					their house painted half white and half yellow. After their deaths, within a
					year of each other, a <title level="m"> Memoir of J. G.</title> (1835) appeared.
						<persName key="John Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abe6d6146-3a0d-42fb-8808-e017d0763beb">John Gilbert</persName> had written the first twenty-six pages, and
						<persName key="Anne Hart Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A162ae917-e7ab-4d72-a60d-c27cbdbcadb7">Anne Hart Gilbert</persName> wrote the remaining eighteen pages. <title level="m">Memoir of J. G</title>. is, in the vein of much nineteenth-century
					life writing, a political and spiritual record, presenting, according to
						<persName>Moira Ferguson</persName> “a holy life that presumes a final
					redemption.” In the process of completing her husband’s memoir, <persName key="Anne Hart Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A162ae917-e7ab-4d72-a60d-c27cbdbcadb7">Gilbert</persName> also documents the “community life” of a biracial couple
					who promote “God’s work”. She writes of her husband, “If there was one<hi rend="italic"> trait</hi> more conspicuous than the rest, amidst the lovely
					harmony of graces visible in his character, it was his <hi rend="italic">total
						renunciation of self</hi>, and<hi rend="italic"> entire dependence on the
						atonement of our blessed Saviour</hi>: and that which made him so remarkable
					as a man, and a man filling an important station in society, was his scrupulous
					integrity, and an openness and candor in all his intercourse with others, which
					even persons not devoid of piety and wisdom thought sometimes carried too far,
					in a disingenuous and unfriendly world.” In the process of documenting the end
					of her husband’s life where he left off, <persName key="Anne Hart Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A162ae917-e7ab-4d72-a60d-c27cbdbcadb7">Anne Hart Gilbert</persName> also offers an account of her own life; far
					from seeking to erase herself from the text, <persName key="Anne Hart Gilbert" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A162ae917-e7ab-4d72-a60d-c27cbdbcadb7">Gilbert</persName> writes in the first person of “I” and in the third of
					“our”, concluding that although “many were made mourners” by her husband’s
					death, “but what are all their losses compared with mine? The lapse of almost
					thirty-five years, with many scenes of sorrow and suffering endured together,
					had cemented our union, and increased the tenderness of our affection to each
					other.” Fletcher, another religious</p>
				<p>Daughters offering reminiscences of their famous writer fathers, grandfathers,
					and husbands form a subset of these filial biographies, many of which have made
					lasting contributions to scholarship on men authors. <persName key="Mary Angela Dickens" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa712a53c-b11d-4140-a69f-442baa6339c9">Mary Angela Dickens</persName> published “A Child’s Memories of Gad’s
					Hill,” which contained her reminiscences of her grandfather, <persName key="Charles Dickens" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A294ea13f-024b-461c-a598-011e649b35fa">Charles Dickens,</persName> in the<title level="m"> Strand Magazine</title>
					in 1897. For many years, <persName key="Anne Thackeray Ritchie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5f0f5485-d14f-4c47-8ee2-6493336c5cb7">Anne Thackeray Ritchie</persName> was best known for her forty-page
					biographical prefaces to the thirteen-volume biographical edition of her father
						<persName key="William Makepeace Thackeray" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A71a8743a-4705-4d4e-8ede-df06c173487f">William Makepeace Thackeray’s</persName> novels. <persName key="Anne Thackeray Ritchie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5f0f5485-d14f-4c47-8ee2-6493336c5cb7">Thackeray</persName> blended literary criticism and biography in a
					conversational style, writing, for example “I cannot help thinking that,
					although Vanity Fair was written in 1845 and the following years, it was really
					begun in 1817, when a little boy, but lately come from
						<placeName>India,</placeName> found himself shut in behind those filigree
					iron gates at <placeName>Chiswick,</placeName> of which he writes when he
					describes Miss Pinkerton's establishment.” Her prefaces form a significant
					contribution to <persName key="Anne Thackeray Ritchie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5f0f5485-d14f-4c47-8ee2-6493336c5cb7">Thackeray</persName> scholarship, establishing authoritative information
					about his life and correcting errors in circulation. <persName key="Anne Thackeray Ritchie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5f0f5485-d14f-4c47-8ee2-6493336c5cb7">Thackeray</persName> was not the only woman to make a long-lasting
					contribution to scholarship in her biographical writings. Frances Kingsley’s
					literary activity centred around the life of her husband, the writer and
					clergyman <persName key="Charles Kingsley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A572f5573-974e-42ce-84d6-c47fac3631f7">Charles Kingsley.</persName> She edited his letters for publication after
					his death, as well as several volumes of his religious writings. Her biography
					of him was wildly successful in the 1870s and 1880s, and remained continuously
					in print until 1983. <persName key="Charles Kingsley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A572f5573-974e-42ce-84d6-c47fac3631f7">Charles Kingsley’s</persName> niece, the travel writer <persName key="Mary Kingsley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ab3f6bc76-fa5f-46f5-a5a7-0ffe73dc137c">Mary Kingsley,</persName> also wrote a memoir of her father, the travel
					writer <persName key="George Henry Kingsley" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0c0106d3-77a3-4520-8e7e-d234b473436d">George Henry Kingsley.</persName> Two sister novelists, <persName key="Florence Marryat" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af5dd2e47-129d-400a-8196-12fb9f393a91">Florence</persName> and <persName key="Augusta Marryat" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5e321f9a-9806-45fe-9d6c-a0c96e683eb6">Augusta Marryat,</persName> worked together on the <title level="m">Life
						and Letters of Captain Marryat </title>(1872) until the collaboration led to
					a quarrel; Marryat, best known for his sea novels, had died when <persName key="Augusta Marryat" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5e321f9a-9806-45fe-9d6c-a0c96e683eb6">Augusta Marryat</persName> was ten years old in 1848.</p>
				<p>More rarely, daughters edited and published their mothers’ life writing. Maria
					Elizabeth is a rare example of a daughter who completed her mother’s memoirs,
					which were posthumously published in four volumes and ended with “A Continuation
					by a Friend.” Maria Elizabeth also edited and posthumously published her
					mother’s <title level="m"> Poetical Works</title> (1806). <persName key="Edith Coleridge" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3e9ed335-d6b8-4773-90da-5656590b112b">Edith Coleridge</persName> prefaced and edited <title level="m">A Memoir
						and Letters of Sara Coleridge</title> (1873); the memoirs themselves
					nevertheless focused on Coleridge’s famous father and his circle rather than
					narrating and interpreting her own experiences. <persName key="Margaret Howitt" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0539ccb9-304c-41fd-8b6f-f03279081b4e">Margaret,</persName>
					<persName key="Mary Howitt" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d6d945c-6ab9-408b-aefb-8fc904593e07">Mary Howitt’s</persName> younger daughter, edited and posthumously
					published <title level="m">Mary Howitt: An Autobiography </title>(1889), with
					illustrations by her artist daughter Anna Mary. <persName key="Lady Louisa Stuart" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adaf4fba2-b0fc-4482-bec6-2d4ef708282c">Lady Louisa Stuart</persName> (1757-1851) wrote memoirs of political
					figures related to her family. <persName key="Lady Louisa Stuart" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adaf4fba2-b0fc-4482-bec6-2d4ef708282c">Stuart,</persName> granddaughter of eighteenth-century writer <persName key="Lady Mary Wortley Montagu" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A843ec1e6-4aba-480a-b57a-e15edd93204e">Lady Mary Wortley Montagu,</persName> published “Introductory Anecdotes” to
					her grandmother’s <title level="m">Letters and Works </title>(1836). Frances
					Eleanor Trollope also wrote about her mother-in-law, the writer Frances Trollope
					(the mother of Anthony Trollope). <title level="m">Frances Trollope: Her Life
						and Literary Work from George III to Victoria </title>(1895) was her
					daughter-in-law’s last publication in a long literary career. Frances Eleanor
					Trollope seems to have been warmly welcomed into this literary family,
					collaborating with her husband Thomas and writing for<title level="m"> Saint
						Paul</title>’s when her famous brother-in-law, Anthony, was editor.
						<persName key="Frances Trollope" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0a30a7df-043e-4e89-a961-ff624251425b">Frances Eleanor Trollope</persName> wrote to publisher Richard Bentley
					regarding the possibility of compiling these memoirs: “I have been looking over
					a great mass of papers relating to <persName key="Frances Trollope" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0a30a7df-043e-4e89-a961-ff624251425b">Frances Trollope.</persName> There is a vast deal of great personal
					interest to the family, and, I think, a considerable amount of matter calculated
					to amuse the public. . . . I cannot refrain from saying that, high as my respect
					for the Mammy (as we always spoke of her en famille) has been ever since I first
					heard or knew anything of her, it has been enormously increased by my perusal of
					these family papers.” Like many family biographers, part of <persName key="Frances Trollope" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0a30a7df-043e-4e89-a961-ff624251425b">Trollope’s</persName> project in writing her mother-in-law’s biography was
					safeguarding her family’s reputation. A main motive was to correct <persName key="Anthony Trollope" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A7458edaa-ca8f-4926-b683-ac0254645c07">Anthony Trollope's</persName> misapprehension about his mother's fidelity
					to her marriage vows. Tidying up family secrets can be read as a feminine
					occupation, and <persName key="Frances Trollope" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0a30a7df-043e-4e89-a961-ff624251425b">Trollope’s</persName> biography of her late mother-in-law shores up her
					status as a dutiful daughter of the family. </p>
				<p>Set against a backdrop of women writers writing predominantly about their
					fathers, husbands, and other male relatives, <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Elizabeth Gaskell’s</persName><title level="m"> Life of Charlotte
						Brontë</title> emerges as a landmark achievement in the history of
					biography. Unlike many nineteenth-century lives and letters, <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell’s</persName> exhaustively researched book–she travelled not only to
					Haworth but also to Brussels in pursuit of her subject–tells <persName key="Charlotte Brontë" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:a017e41e-6e1c-4c16-a575-82d25f7ec038">Brontë’s</persName> life story in novelistic detail. In the process,
						<persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell</persName> contributes to the Brontë myth of the three sister
					novelists leading a “wild and struggling and isolated life” in Haworth
					parsonage. Through readings of contemporary newspapers, twentieth-century
					scholarship has shown that nineteenth-century Yorkshire was considerably less
					isolated than the Brontës and their first biographers suggested. Nonetheless,
						<persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell’s</persName> portrait of the sisters as passionate and isolated
					continues to exert enormous influence over the view of the Brontës in the
					popular imagination to this day. “Wild, strong hearts, and powerful minds, were
					hidden under an enforced propriety and regularity of demeanour and expression,”
						<persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell</persName> writes of the sisters, suggesting a duality between
					their restrained public selves and their private writing selves. </p>
				<p><persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell’s</persName> innovation in biographical form creates a cohesive
					narrative more similar to twentieth-century biography than many
					nineteenth-century biographies which intersperse brief bits of context between
					letters. Linda Peterson has argued that <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell</persName> develops a “separate streams” approach to describe the
					life of her fellow writer, in which her home life and professional writing life
					flow alongside each other without necessarily causing any undue anxiety. In
					contrast to second wave feminist criticism, in which critics including Gubar and
					Gilbert argued that women writers like <persName key="Charlotte Brontë" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:a017e41e-6e1c-4c16-a575-82d25f7ec038">Brontë</persName> experienced an anxiety of authorship around reconciling
					the competing identities of woman and writer, Peterson argues that these
					separate streams in life did not cause undue anxiety for many women writers,
					including <persName key="Charlotte Brontë" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:a017e41e-6e1c-4c16-a575-82d25f7ec038">Charlotte Brontë.</persName>
					<persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell</persName> herself takes a middle road in her depiction of
						<persName key="Charlotte Brontë" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:a017e41e-6e1c-4c16-a575-82d25f7ec038">Brontë.</persName> She does see a separation between the woman and the
					writer but argues that these differences were not impossible to reconcile:
					“Charlotte Brontë's existence becomes divided into two parallel currents—her
					life as Currer Bell, the author; her life as Charlotte Brontë, the woman. There
					were separate duties belonging to each character—not opposing each other; not
					impossible, but difficult to be reconciled.” It is different, <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell</persName> argues, for male writers, “When a man becomes an author,
					it is probably merely a change of employment to him. He takes a portion of that
					time which has hitherto been devoted to some other study or pursuit . . . and
					another merchant or lawyer, or doctor, steps into his vacant place, and probably
					does as well as he.” For <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell,</persName> women’s duties differ from men’s professional lives in
					that each woman fulfils a unique place in her family life, such that “no other
					can take up the quiet, regular duties of the daughter, the wife, or the mother”.
					Women must not “drop the domestic charges devolving on her as an individual, for
					the exercise of the most splendid talents that were ever bestowed. And yet she
					must not shrink from the extra responsibility implied by the very fact of her
					possessing such talents.” <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell</persName> was well-compensated for writing <title level="m">The
						Life of Charlotte Brontë</title>, earning £800 and an additional £200 for an
					extensively revised third edition. (She donated £100 to buy a much-needed new
					parish pump in the village of Haworth.) While the bulk of <persName key="Elizabeth Gaskell" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A19a1e66b-a359-47ce-b49e-372f35196d42">Gaskell’s</persName> writerly output was fiction, in the nineteenth
					century, some professional women writers began making biography, and especially
					collective biography, a significant genre in their careers. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Collective Biography</head>
				<p>One form in which women’s biography written by women flourished in the nineteenth
					century was collective biography. One reason collective biography has flourished
					is that it gathers many women’s lives rather than highlighting one life,
					typically focusing each chapter on a different subject. Writing one chapter on a
					woman rather than an entire book can help a writer overcome material challenges
					in the way of writing women’s lives, including a lack of biographical material
					as well as sexist beliefs that women’s lives merit attention in the aggregate,
					as an inspiration to womankind, but not sustained attention on an individual
					level. Collective biography may be a particularly feminist form. As Alison Booth
					has argued, the collection of multiple lives helps us resist the prototypical
					nineteenth century life-writing narrative of the heroic individual. Because the
					form presents multiple lives, the narratives also “challenge the claim to
					represent universal womanhood”. Finally, “group biographies,” Booth argues,
					“suggest the interdependence and social construction of identities.” Like the
					early lives of saints, collective biographies of women often aim to inspire
					readers to emulate the lives of their subjects; they can also serve as a
					feminist rebuttal to claims of women’s inferiority. Such was the first
					collective biography of women by a woman, <persName key="Christine de Pizan">Christine de Pizan’</persName>s <title level="m">Le livre de la cité des
						dames</title> (1405), which mounted a defence of women through collective
					biography. The 1521 English translation published by<persName key="Henry Pepywell"> Henry Pepywell</persName>, 1521 as <title level="m">The Boke of the Cyte of Ladyes,</title> was much discussed in its own day.
					Unfortunately, <persName key="Christine de Pizan">Pizan</persName> and <title level="m">The City of Ladies</title> had fallen out of history by the late
					eighteenth century when <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Mary Hays</persName> began pondering her collective biography, writing in
					the <title level="m">Monthly Magazine</title> around 1796 about the need for an
					inspiring collection of women’s lives.</p>
				<p>The result of her thinking, published six years later in 1802, was the six-volume
					work, <title level="m">Female Biography; or, Memoirs of Illustrious and
						Celebrated Women, of All Ages and Countries. Alphabetically
					Arranged</title>. The fashion for collective biography in <placeName>Great
						Britain </placeName>came from <placeName>France</placeName> in the early
					nineteenth century. <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Hays’s</persName> experience in researching and writing <title level="m">Female Biography </title>illustrates the challenges women writers faced at
					the turn of the nineteenth-century in researching and writing about the lives of
					other women. One problem was education. <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Hays</persName> lacked the classical education and “formal training in the
					conventions of scholarship” of many of her male contemporaries; in a work with
					302 entries on women across the globe, <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Hays</persName> knew only French and English, and had difficulty in
					accessing rare books and scholarship on her subjects. Another problem in
					researching her collective biography was the dearth of information on even
					historically significant women’s lives; this lack of sources on women’s lives,
					which have often been considered too trivial and mundane to document, continues
					to challenge would-be biographers of women to this day. This lack of
					documentation of women’s lives speaks to the attitude that their lives were not
					worth a biography. Finally, <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Hays</persName> had few models to emulate in researching and writing her
						<title level="m">Female Biography</title>: Ann Thicknesse's <title level="m">Sketches of the Lives and Writings of the Ladies of France</title>, 1778
					was the only other woman-authored collective biography already published in
					English. Despite these challenges, <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Hays’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Female Biography</title> was an enormous success that pointed
					the way forward for other female (and feminist) forms of life writing. <title level="m">Female Biography</title> was influential throughout the nineteenth
					century: its entries were often reproduced without attribution (or plagiarised)
					throughout. It also arguably set a trend for other collective biographies of
					women throughout the nineteenth century.</p>
				<p>Women writers throughout the nineteenth century followed <persName key="Mary Hays" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Af4d8ae18-12a9-40e7-930d-8b9386d45ad0">Mary Hays’s</persName> example in writing collective biography. Sisters
						<persName key="Agnes Strickland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6eb0d93d-fbce-4d6f-bd73-da1c0129d50a">Agnes</persName> and <persName key="Elizabeth Strickland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa818cea6-e440-4784-a965-0e5d213ff62e">Elizabeth Strickland</persName> co-authored the twelve-volume <title level="m">Lives of the Queens of England, from the Norman Conquest</title>,
					which appeared from 1840 to 1848. (Only <persName key="Agnes Strickland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6eb0d93d-fbce-4d6f-bd73-da1c0129d50a">Agnes’s</persName> name appeared on the title page.) ^Through the lives of
					33 queens, few of whom had received much scholarly attention, and some of whose
					lives had, like Mary of Modena, never been written at all, the Strickland
					sisters argued that queens were important historical actors in their own right,
					and not, as some historians had argued, mere tools for the ambition and
					abilities of men. They put forth the thesis that as women, queens had exercised
					a civilizing feminine influence as instruments of moral and religious
					improvement. The twelve volumes were an ambitious research project, and the
					Strickland sisters lobbied politicians and pulled strings to secure entry into
					the State Paper Office, which did not normally admit women. There they were able
					to discover and identify official documents which had never been published.^
						<title level="m">The Queens of England</title> was an enormous success, and
					received attention from eminent biographers of the twentieth century, including
						<persName key="Antonia Fraser" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Acb3e68e4-a54b-4650-b598-86cd8eb70084">Antonia Fraser</persName> and <persName key="Peter Ackroyd" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aaab7424c-5027-4e33-910e-210fa76f165e">Peter Ackroyd.</persName> In the wake of this success, the Strickland
					sisters continued to write collective biographies, including <title level="m">Lives of the Queens of Scotland</title> (1850-1859), <title level="m">Lives
						of the Bachelor Kings of England </title>(1861), <title level="m">The Lives
						of the Seven Bishops Committed to the Tower in 1688 </title>(1866), and
						<title level="m">Lives of the Tudor Princesses </title>(1868). Other
					collective biographies included <persName key="Anna Jameson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A467a52fa-7cb0-448b-bd87-64bc7a2e9973">Anna Jameson’s</persName>
					<title level="m">The Beauties of the Court of King Charles the Second</title>
					(1826) and <title level="m">Memoirs of Celebrated Female Sovereigns</title>
					(1831), <persName key="Louisa Costello" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A67ebde5a-ca69-4e85-8a91-0d2d33bb8055">Louisa Costello’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Lives of Eminent Englishwomen</title> (1844), and <persName key="Rosa Nouchette Carey" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa20e9eea-1c7b-4baa-bf6e-b729beabd9a2">Rosa Nouchette Cary’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Twelve Notable Good Women of the XIXth Century: With Twelve
						Portraits </title>(1899). Echoing many of her peers, <persName key="Rosa Nouchette Carey" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aa20e9eea-1c7b-4baa-bf6e-b729beabd9a2">Cary</persName> hoped her readers would emulate the (mainly royal) lives
					she wrote about: “sketches of twelve noble and useful lives be read and studied
					by women of this generation, and go and do thou likewise be written upon some
					true heart.”</p>
				<p>While most of these collective biographies focus on white, middle-class or
					aristocratic women, there is also more room in the form for the representation
					of racialized, ethnic, or lower class women. In 1822, the Irish Quaker author
						<persName key="Mary Leadbeater" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A126f5ba1-4b8b-4be5-9e44-33c984972369">Mary Leadbeater</persName> published <title level="m">Cottage Biography,
						Being a Collection of Lives of the Irish Peasantry</title>. This collection
					of very brief biographies, some no more than a page, written in prose and
					sometimes incorporating verse, highlights the ordinary experience of the
					individuals that <persName key="Mary Leadbeater" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A126f5ba1-4b8b-4be5-9e44-33c984972369">Leadbeater</persName> knew in and around her native Ballitore, a village in
					County Kildare, Ireland. Her biographical subjects experience disability (more
					than one person is blinded by accident), seduction, and hard labour. Her women’s
					lives are rich in cultural detail: one fallen woman brings up her illegitimate
					daughter alone and cares for her invalid sister; the father never contributes to
					their support, though he never marries, but finally makes his daughter heiress
					to two acres of land. In another story of informal adoption, a schoolmaster’s
					widow takes care of the daughter of another widow for twelve years, keeping the
					child as her own after the other widow cannot pay her. When the birth mother
					kidnaps her at age twelve, the foster mother is panic-stricken until she manages
					to rescue her. Another couple waits for twenty years to marry, until the
					disapproving mother, who wanted a better match for her carpenter son than a
					maidservant, finally relents.</p>
				<p>Most collective biographies are comprised of white, Christian, women, with a
					possible exception for Asian or Indigenous women, including Zenobia, Cleopatra
					and Pocahontas, who appear as famous rulers, beauties of rank, or models of the
					“benefits of Christianity and European education.” In the U.S., some collective
					lives of Black women began to appear at the end of the nineteenth century, but
					in Britain racialized subjects generally appeared as one among many women.
						<persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Grace Aguilar’s</persName>
					<title level="m">The Women of Israel</title> provides a notable exception to the
					almost entirely Christian collective biographies of women. Like her Christian
					counterparts, <persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Aguilar</persName> uses collective biography to provide her readers with
					examples of good Jewish women to emulate. <persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Aguilar’s</persName> subjects in her first volume are biblical, from Eve to
					Hannah, and she argues that because they have mainly been written about by
					Christian writers, “for the women of Israel something still more is needed.”
						<persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Aguilar</persName> anticipates arguments that her book may, in parts
					“resemble more a religious essay than female biography” replying that “the vital
					spirit of religion, is the sole intention of these pages.” <persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Aguilar’s</persName> interpretation of biblical stories draws on the male
					Jewish tradition of Midrash or scriptural commentary; some scholars have argued
					that <persName key="Grace Aguilar" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d7f95d6-55b6-4556-9224-1b110676f09f">Aguilar</persName> may have been the first Jewish woman to write in the
					tradition. <title level="m">The Women of Israel</title> went through many
					editions, and remained in circulation as a prize in both Sunday School.
					Collective biographies of women grew in popularity throughout the nineteenth
					century. The number of titles published per year roughly tripled from the 1830s,
					when 7 to 9 titles per year appeared, to the 1880s and 1890s, when more than
					thirty collected lives of women were published per year.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Memoir</head>
				<p>By the end of the century, one of the dominant modes of women’s life writing was
					the memoir. Memoirs in the nineteenth century took a different form from the
					autobiographical narratives about the arc of one particular life experience or
					event we know in the twenty-first century. In her work on nineteenth-century
					women’s life writing, <persName key="Mary Jean Corbett">Mary Jean
						Corbett</persName> defines memoirs as works that offer an account of
					historical events or people through the first-person account of a writer who was
					there and who knew the people in question. As such, they walk the line between
					autobiography, which offers a first person account of the writer's own life, and
					biography, a researched account where the author may or may not know the
					historical figures in question, and where the author is less likely to make an
					appearance in the text. Memoirs offered late Victorian literary women a way to
					recount their personal experiences without centering themselves or revealing
					their own secrets. As <persName key="Mary Jean Corbett">Corbett</persName>
					writes, “its self-displacing characteristics make it a form with which many seem
					to have felt subjective affinities. The formal properties of memoir enable its
					practitioners both to speak and to remain silent about themselves, almost in the
					same gesture, by focusing on others.” <persName key="Valerie Sanders">Valerie
						Sanders</persName> notes that the speakers of memoirs tend to situate
					themselves as reporters of outmoded practices and impressions of the famous,
					while putting their own lives to the side. Memoirs, often written by those
					adjacent to well-known historical figures and celebrities who are not as famous
					themselves, purport to offer an insider’s view of what happened. For example,
						<persName key="Marguerite Gardiner" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aea8282fb-e8ea-48a3-81c0-9c4a0f7d5ea0">Marguerite Gardiner,</persName> Countess of Blessington, made her
					reputation on <title level="m">Conversations of Lord Byron with the Countess of
						Blessington </title>(1834). A fluent and perceptive retailer of gossip, she
					confides to the reader about her first meeting of <persName key="Lord Alfred Byron" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abac6654a-c685-4e61-bb95-09a53a56f401">Byron</persName>: “I had fancied him taller, with a more dignified and
					commanding air; and I looked in vain for the hero-looking sort of person with
					whom I had so long identified him in imagination.” The resulting text feels as
					though it gives authentic access to Byron. </p>
				<p><persName key="Mary Jean Corbett">Corbett</persName> argues that for women “the
					memoir legitimates the telling of their own lives without demanding that they
					commit full disclosure”; which could make the memoir an appealing genre for
					writers attempting to adhere to middle-class standards of feminine modesty,
					while nonetheless committing their thoughts to paper. The result is often, as
						<persName key="Mary Jean Corbett">Corbett</persName> argues of <persName key="Anne Thackeray Ritchie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5f0f5485-d14f-4c47-8ee2-6493336c5cb7">Anne Thackeray Ritchie</persName>, “a self in process and in relation who
					is revealed only in what she reveals about others.” <persName key="Mary Russell Mitford" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5ba9d086-43c9-4b7c-9e4e-1404286974ea">Mary Russell Mitford’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Recollections of a Literary Life; or, Books, Places and People
					</title>(1852), was published three years before her death. <title level="m">Recollections</title> mixes local scene-painting, criticism, extracts, and
					of course, literary gossip: she recorded stories of writers in her wide circle
					including <persName key="Felicia Hemans" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A7ed5a809-36e6-47a6-a72c-3ac6332186cf">Felicia Hemans,</persName>
					<persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/cwrc%3Ae313ed1b-e2c5-48e1-a7a5-b83cde7968d4">Harriet Martineau</persName>, and <persName key="Catherine Fanshawe" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A76d97298-fbdf-4cca-a046-8938fef833ae">Catherine Fanshawe</persName>. <persName key="Elizabeth Barrett Browning" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:7fa078f1-e346-4d74-a9c4-4e3e57e80cad">Elizabeth Barrett Browning</persName> and <persName key="Robert Browning" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A6315e747-c757-448c-be99-8f4a8ca854ad">Robert Browning</persName> were dismayed at <hi rend="bold">[by] </hi>the
					violation of their privacy in <persName key="Mary Russell Mitford" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5ba9d086-43c9-4b7c-9e4e-1404286974ea">Mitford’s</persName> work. <persName key="Eliza Lynn Linton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A73c9e3bc-f973-4875-ac18-8f51df9aba97">Eliza Lynn Linton’s</persName>
					<title level="m">My Literary Life</title> (1899), edited by her literary
					goddaughter <persName key="Beatrice Harraden" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8bbb9a03-3e40-40dc-9c15-6cd482dafa3c">Beatrice Harraden,</persName> contains so little about herself that it has
					also been titled <title level="m">Reminiscences of Dickens, <persName key="Anne Thackeray Ritchie" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5f0f5485-d14f-4c47-8ee2-6493336c5cb7">Thackeray</persName>, George Eliot, etc.</title>
				</p>
				<p><persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Camilla Crosland’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Landmarks of a Literary Life </title>(1893) offers a case study
					of a working writer whose reminiscences legitimise her career without centering
					herself. Unlike men writers who offer a story of their personal struggle to
					become a working writer, beginning with telling incidents in their childhood,
					detailing a period of apprenticeship and culminating in their literary success,
						<persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Crosland</persName> tells a story of a sociable literary self whose career
					is deeply imbricated with those of the other writers, especially women writers,
					whom she knew and worked with. Corbett argues that <persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Crosland</persName> positions herself as an historian of the everyday:
					“Unlike Carlyle and his contemporaries, who saw history as the collective
					biography of great men, Crosland sees history happening in and through all
					individuals, each of whom has some story to tell… By conferring on everyone the
					potential capacity from particular points of view, Crosland suggests that the
					history of each individual, whether elite or obscure, has some value for
					readers. Every person is presumed to possess a distinct subjectivity, a
					particular vantage point”. <persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Crosland</persName> asserts that her task will not be to “inflict my
					autobiography on the reader.” “It will be my aim,” she writes, “ to keep the
					obtrusive personal pronoun “I” very considerably in the background; yet I know
					that I must speak of myself sometimes in connection with scenes I shall try to
					describe.” <title level="m">Landmarks of a Literary Life</title> looks over a
					life and career whose early memories include the Battle of Waterloo and the
					struggles of Queen Caroline, and which focuses on the development of a
					professional writing career in London of the 1840s. The “landmarks” of <persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Crosland’s</persName> literary life are not her own publications, but
					rather her interactions with other writers, publishers, editors and artists.
						<persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Crosland</persName> structures her adult recollections largely around the
					dinner parties, conversaziones, and at-homes that introduced her to literary
						<placeName>London</placeName> mainly in the 1840s. Through <persName key="Camilla Crosland" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ae97db1f2-9f06-4368-bbdd-79ba978020cb">Crosland’s</persName> recollections, the importance of such literary
					sociability in enabling women writers to make a living becomes clear. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Autobiography </head>
				<p>For most of the nineteenth century, some of the most common forms of women’s
					autobiography were the spiritual autobiography, which often focused on spiritual
					awakening, and the <title level="m">chroniques scandaleuses</title> of
					actresses, who wrote about their love affairs. Spiritual autobiography crossed
					class lines, and was the most common form of working class women’s life writing.
						<persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Harriet Martineau’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Autobiography</title> has been seen as adhering most closely to
					the more masculine forms of the spiritual autobiography crossed with the
					vocational narrative. Some women writers wrote autobiographies as children.
						<persName key="Florence Nightingale" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A55ac16d5-7dd1-40d4-95f5-2324fe707e70">Florence Nightingale</persName> wrote “La vie de Florence Rossignol,” in
					French no less, between the ages of eight and ten. <persName key="Elizabeth Barrett Browning" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A7fa078f1-e346-4d74-a9c4-4e3e57e80cad">Elizabeth Barrett Browning</persName> wrote an essay, “Glimpses into my own
					Life and Literary Character,” aged 13. Women who had experienced extraordinarily
					difficult circumstances also wrote autobiography in the form of works supported
					by subscribers and meant to help with their financial situation. The is the
					framework that legitimates works ranging from <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Mary Seacole’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Wonderful Adventures</title> to power loom weaver <persName key="Ellen Johnston" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ad48be0a4-0469-476d-8c75-a04755eb53d0">Ellen Johnston’s</persName> autobiographical preface to her book of poetry.
					In the final decades of the nineteenth century and the first decades of the
					twentieth century, autobiographies of women writers began to appear in print for
					the first time. Works by <persName key="Mary Howitt" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d6d945c-6ab9-408b-aefb-8fc904593e07">Mary Howitt,</persName>
					<persName key="Margaret Oliphant" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9308c943-ac98-4296-bd0d-03e4149578fa">Margaret Oliphant,</persName>
					<persName key="Mary Augusta Ward" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A50ebb38b-92ab-4fa8-b23a-16d918902fd3">Mary Augusta Ward</persName> and others blended the tropes of the domestic
					novel and the vocational narrative of the artist.</p>
				<p>The spiritual memoir was among the most common forms of women’s autobiographical
					writing in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth century; religious discourse
					could legitimise women’s lives in print, and cut across class lines, with
					working-class women as well as middle-class women writing in the genre. In the
					seventeenth century, there was a tradition of non-conformist spiritual
					autobiography that was not predicated on gender: both women and men treat their
					lives as a struggle between opposing forces, and delineate their spiritual
					progress, making little mention of their domestic lives. By the nineteenth
					century, however, women’s spiritual autobiography became increasingly
					domesticated. <persName key="Charlotte Elizabeth Tonna" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8fb1fa10-bf2a-4da0-900a-5f7a975aac9d">Charlotte Elizabeth Tonna’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Personal Recollections</title> are among the best-known
					spiritual autobiographies by a woman writer in the nineteenth century. <persName key="Charlotte Elizabeth Tonna" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8fb1fa10-bf2a-4da0-900a-5f7a975aac9d">Tonna</persName> was a popular author of didactic works for children in the
					nineteenth century, and she is now remembered mainly for her denunciation of the
					women factory workers forced to work outside the home; or what she called “the
					monstrous abuse of forcing the female to forsake her proper sphere.” Her
					spiritual biography takes an epistolary form: it is written as fourteen letters.
					Unusually, <persName key="Charlotte Elizabeth Tonna" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8fb1fa10-bf2a-4da0-900a-5f7a975aac9d">Tonna</persName> published her autobiography when she was fifty-one and in
					good health, in an attempt to forestall any unauthorised versions of her life.
					Anxious that a would-be biographer would write her life “wholly unenlightened by
					spiritual knowledge, and uninfluenced by spiritual feeling” and disapproving of
					the way in which “Private journals are sought out, confidential letters raked
					together, and a most unseemly exposure made, alike of the living and the dead”
					she asked all her correspondents to keep their letters out of biographer’s
					hands, and wrote the story of her life herself. Writing about working class
					women’s spiritual autobiographies, <persName key="Jane Rendall" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Acf5adfeb-059b-4e1b-a3be-ff2065f32851">Jane Rendall</persName> notes that they cut across religious denominations
					and tended to tell the story of an individual seeking enlightenment through a
					life of “constant self-abegnation and self-exploration.” Encouraged by a
					minister, Mary Saxby wrote her religious tract <title level="m">Memoirs of a
						Female Vagrant </title>(1806), to show the “vices and miseries of a vagrant
					life.” </p>
				<p>Any instruction that working-class women authors received was on religion or
					domestic skills, and <persName key="Florence Boos" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A5b398265-3919-4ad9-8237-73e89acfa267">Florence Boos</persName> notes that working-class women writers left school
					by age twelve, if not much earlier. Their autobiographies were written for
					family members and often left incomplete due to circumstances. They wrote more
					about sexuality, courtship and family life than their male counterparts, who
					seldom mentioned their wives or children. Common themes in these autobiographies
					included extreme food deprivation, and physical and sexual abuse and assault
					from employers, parents, husbands, and sometime their own grown children.
					Working-class women writers were often poets but published little fiction; one
					common form that their autobiographies tend to take is a brief autobiographical
					preface to a collection of poetry, complete with a frontispiece portrait of the
					author. Like much nineteenth-century women’s life writing, a few of these came
					to light in the twentieth century, providing historians with relatively rare
					first hand accounts of the lives of working-class women. <persName key="Ellen Weeton" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A05090d81-1edf-4bf7-bbe7-c47bcf0744e5">Ellen Weeton</persName> (1776-1844), an abused wife whose husband beat her
					almost to death, obtained a separation to save her life, but it cost her
					visitation rights to her daughter. In 1822, she wrote an autobiographical
					sketch, “A Retrospect,” for her daughter, who was only six years old. She went
					on to publish another autobiographical sketch two years later: both were
					published more than one hundred years after her death as <title level="m">Miss
						Weeton’s Journal of a Governess </title>(1869). Ellen Johnston (1835-1874),
					also known as the “Factory Girl” was one ^of the few working-class Victorian
					women whose poetry made it into print in volume form.^ Having published her
					poetry in local newspapers, the <title level="m">Autobiography, Poems, and Songs
						of Ellen Johnston, the 'Factory Girl'</title> were published by subscription
					in Glasgow. <persName key="Ellen Johnston" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ad48be0a4-0469-476d-8c75-a04755eb53d0">Johnston,</persName> a power-loom weaver who worked in factories from age
					eleven, intimates in her short autobiographical sketch, a preface to her book of
					poetry, that she was sexually abused by her stepfather. As a teenager, she
					became proud, single mother of an illegitimate daughter <persName key="Mary Achenvole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ac25802a9-dfb5-4c9d-b55d-0aef26c65d78">Mary Achenvole</persName>; her mother took care of her baby while she wrote
					poetry for newspapers, which proved lucrative. She stoutly rejects Goldsmith's
					assertion that a woman who has stooped to folly can only die, writing, “I did
					not, however, feel inclined to die when I could no longer conceal what the world
					falsely calls a woman's shame.” Her pregnancy and her daughter's birth inspired
					her with new hopes for life. <persName key="Ellen Johnston" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ad48be0a4-0469-476d-8c75-a04755eb53d0">Johnston</persName> not only got her short autobiography into print, but
					she also pushed back against the imposition of bourgeois standards for
					femininity for interpreting her life.</p>
				<p>Actresses’s autobiographies also tended to push against the limits of bourgeois
					femininity, perhaps in part because they had already exposed themselves in the
					public imagination by being on stage. Peterson has argued that the publication
					of the lives of actors is part of a shift from earlier metaphors of life as a
					pilgrimage to metaphors of life as a stage. <persName key="Mary Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aaa492a9d-44ee-49b9-98ba-d06e0018634f">Mary Robinson’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Memoirs</title> (1801) were published in four volumes the year
					after her death. <persName key="William D. Brewer" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aad97a5ae-295d-4f8a-86f9-b9aa7b25b8df">William D. Brewer</persName> has recently read <persName key="Mary Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aaa492a9d-44ee-49b9-98ba-d06e0018634f">Robinson’s</persName> memoirs as a disability autobiography. <persName key="Mary Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aaa492a9d-44ee-49b9-98ba-d06e0018634f">Robinson’s</persName> health collapsed in her mid-twenties, after a bout of
					rheumatic fever or rheumatoid arthritis left her progressively paralysed.
						<persName key="Mary Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aaa492a9d-44ee-49b9-98ba-d06e0018634f">Robinson</persName> had been an actress and the mistress of the Prince of
					Wales before becoming a radical writer of novels, drama, periodical essays and
					poetry. Some of her contemporaries read her disability as an appropriate
					punishment for a fallen woman. (It was rumoured that her paralysis was the
					result of abortion, venereal disease, or an infection following a miscarriage.)
					Others read her disability as an atonement for her sins. In the memoir,
						<persName key="Mary Robinson" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Aaa492a9d-44ee-49b9-98ba-d06e0018634f">Robinson</persName> represents herself as a romantic heroine, and at times,
					as a victim. She wrote that she had never experienced a single year of
					happiness. She did not regret the feeling that she had not long to live: I feel
					my health decaying, my spirit broken. She left the memoirs unfinished at her
					death: <hi rend="bold">the narrative </hi>broken off just before she became the
					prince's mistress. She made her daughter solemnly promise to publish them. Later
					in the century, the actress <persName key="Fanny Kemble" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adaeb189c-6470-4cb8-ac0a-82979b81faf8">Fanny Kemble</persName> published several volumes of life writing,
					including <title level="m">Record of a Girlhood: An Autobiography</title>
					(1878), a collection of previously published articles about her youth. This
					successful collection was followed by <title level="m">Records of Later
						Life</title> (1882) and <title level="m">Further Records, 1848-1883: A
						series of letters . . . forming a sequel to Record of a Girlhood and Records
						of Later Life </title>(1890).</p>
				<p><persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Harriet Martineau</persName> is the woman writer who published an
					autobiography that hews most closely to the masculine traditions of spiritual
					chronicle and bildungsroman leading to a vocation as a writer. <ref target="#rresponse">In <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau’s</persName> case, her religious exploration leads her not to
						faith but to agnosticism. Linda H. Peterson argues that <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau’s</persName>
						<title level="m">Autobiography</title> is a response to the domestic memoir,
						and to the domestication of religion and intellect in memoirs of women
						including <persName key="Charlotte Elizabeth Tonna" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A8fb1fa10-bf2a-4da0-900a-5f7a975aac9d">Charlotte Tonna</persName> and <persName key="Maria Edgeworth" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Ace9dd632-a24f-4deb-ba9c-3c1e9f0c3d05">Maria Edgeworth.</persName></ref> She writes that <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau’s</persName> text invokes an “older, purer form of spiritual
					autobiography that focuses on theological crisis and spiritual growth,”
					resulting in an autobiography “more public and professional” than any before
					Anthony Trollope's in 1883, or George Augusta Sala's in 1894. The bildungsroman
					aspect of <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau’s</persName> autobiography focuses on her education,
					intellectual, and spiritual development. <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau,</persName> who was brought up in a Unitarian family and
					benefited from the education available to women in dissenting circles in
					Norwich, fits her own intellectual development into a Comtean framework as she
					moves through an early stage of religious faith, through a metaphysical fog, and
					finally, in her late thirties, to a “positivistic stage of thought.” <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> reframes her autobiography not as an invasion of
					privacy but as a “duty.” She insists that she has “no solicitude about fame and
					no fear of my reputation of any sort being injured by the publication of
					anything I have ever put to paper.” Having forbidden her friends and family to
					publish her letters (many ignored her prohibition), and believing she was dying,
						<persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> set out to fulfil her duty and write her
					autobiography. She believed that “certain qualities of my own mind,--a strong
					consciousness and a clear memory in regard to my early feelings,--have seemed to
					indicate to the duty of my recording my own experience.” Her delineation of
					these qualities of her mind, justified her Autobiography, which was published
					when she actually died twenty years later and finished by her literary executor,
						<persName key="Maria Weston Chapman" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Afbbd9a2d-125e-4295-ad54-cce3f3143206">Maria Weston Chapman</persName>. As Peterson has argued, for <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau,</persName> gender was far from the foremost consideration in her
					mind as she wrote her autobiography. And yet, <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Autobiography</title> is in part a landmark text because it is
					one of the only autobiographies by women published in the nineteenth century
					that, in its very existence, makes the argument that the delineation of a
					woman’s mind, her spiritual and intellectual progress, is worthy as the subject
					of a monograph.</p>
				<p><persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau’s</persName>
					<title level="m">Autobiography</title>, in tandem with her earlier work, <title level="m">Life in the Sickroom</title>, also offers her perspective on
					illness and disability. Periods of illness and disability require more extensive
					care and dependence, further highlighting the relational model of the self that
					is so central to women’s life writing. <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> experienced an extended period of invalidism: for six
					years she was confined to her bed. Maria Frawley has argued that <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> presents the life of the invalid as full of
					opportunities for introspection. As <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> writes: “Nothing is more impossible to represent in
					words, even to one’s self in meditative moments, than what it is to lie on the
					verge of life and watch, with nothing to do but think, and learn from what we
					behold.” <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau,</persName> who lost much of her hearing as a teenager, used an
					ear trumpet. While contemporary work in disability studies and the ethics of
					care tends to value interdependence, <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> writes about her deafness as an opportunity for
					self-sufficiency. Knowing more than one other deaf woman who has supposedly
					become a nuisance to others because of her need to ask for information to be
					repeated, <persName key="Harriet Martineau" ref="https://commons.cwrc.ca/orlando:ad6c2ea8-cac6-40e2-b1d3-85db36795381">Martineau</persName> made a resolution to never ask her friends to repeat
					themselves. She writes that she is “confident that this same deafness is about
					the best thing that ever happened to me;--the best, in a selfish view, as the
					grandest impulse to self-mastery; and the best in a higher view, as my most
					peculiar opportunity of helping others, who suffer the same misfortune without
					equal stimulus to surmount the false shame, and other unspeakable miseries which
					attend it.”</p>
				<p><persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Mary Seacole’s</persName> autobiography, the <title level="m">Wonderful
						Adventures of Mrs. Seacole in Many Lands</title>, combines life writing and
					travel writing, and was legitimised in part as a plea for financial help.
						<persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> felt compelled to publish in part because having cared
					for British soldiers in the <placeName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7835">Crimea</placeName>, she was now bankrupt, and was urged by a committee of
					“noblemen and gentlemen” who knew her in the Crimea and came together to aid her
					to write her story. <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole’s</persName> supporters included <persName key="Queen Victoria" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A68336d67-737e-4d46-9625-140373914ce8">Queen Victoria’s</persName> cousin H.S.H. Prince Edward of Saxe Weimar and
					the <title level="m">Times</title> correspondent from the Crimea, W. H. Russell.
					Remarkably, <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> constructs a text that tells her own story from her
					birth and parentage to the present moment, and centres her own experience,
					desires, and opinions. <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole,</persName> a free woman and mobile subject, records that she was
					born in <placeName ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q34692">Kingston,
						Jamaica,</placeName> a “Creole” with “good Scotch blood coursing in my
					veins,” through her father, a soldier from an old Scottish family. While
					subscribing to some extent to the stereotype of Scottish people as practical and
					hardworking, she protests against Caribbean stereotypes: “I have often heard the
					term ‘lazy Creole’ applied to my country people; but I am sure I do not know
					what it is to be indolent.” <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole’s</persName> mother kept a boarding house and was also, <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> recounts, like many Creole women, an “admirable
					doctress”.” The story that <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> tells about herself is that of a persistent and skilled
					medical professional and entrepreneur. More than half of the <title level="m">Wonderful Adventures</title> details <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole’s</persName> experience in the Crimea, and she remains best known
					today as a heroine of the Crimea alongside Florence Nightingale. In a reversal
					of the trope of Britain as the motherland to the West Indies, <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> presents herself as a colonial mother to her ‘sons’ in
					the army, with the authority of both motherhood and medical experience.
					Infamously, Nightingale and the War Office turned <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole’s</persName> offer of her medical expertise down, likely because
					she was mixed race. In the face of racist rejection she maintains a sense of her
					own value: “War, I know, is a serious game, but sometimes very humble actors are
					of great use in it”. Unusually, <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> published her autobiography in her lifetime, on her
					return from the Crimea, but it was soon forgotten. Her story only came back to
					light in the 1980s, when two editions of <title level="m">Wonderful Adventures
					</title>appeared more than 120 years after its first publication. <persName key="Mary Seacole" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Abed4478f-aedf-4555-afc6-7917863eff41">Seacole</persName> achieved heroine status in the twenty-first century: in
					both Jamaica and England plaques have been erected in her honour, and she has
					been the subject of multiple biographies.^ </p>
				<p>As more middle-class women took up work outside of the home, the end of the
					nineteenth century and the beginning of the twentieth century saw new forms of
					autobiography: including, the emergence of autobiographies of women writers. The
					autobiographies of women writers often explored the conflict between women’s
					domestic duties and their literary labour. Domestic patterns, including the
					plots of sisterhood, motherhood, and conjugal life, made their way into the
					autobiographies of later nineteenth century women writers. In her <title level="m">Autobiography</title> (1889), <persName key="Mary Howitt" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A3d6d945c-6ab9-408b-aefb-8fc904593e07">Mary Howitt</persName> presents her hack writing, which she took on so that
					her husband William could do more literary work, as “part of her wifely duty as
					helpmeet “simultaneously legitimating it and undercutting it.” <persName key="Margaret Oliphant" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9308c943-ac98-4296-bd0d-03e4149578fa">Margaret Oliphant</persName> similarly claimed in her <title level="m">Autobiography</title> (1889) that she had no pretensions to being a great
					writer like <persName key="George Eloit" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Adca30947-feee-44db-820e-bbcc21038396">George Eliot</persName> or <persName key="George Sand" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A99dca4bc-1699-467f-8d10-ec1597548aca">George Sand</persName>. Setting motherhood and genius in opposition, she
					claimed to value herself as a mother rather than a writer. She wrote that it
					suited her temperament better, “to drive on and keep everything going” to
					support her family after the death of her husband rather than to “labour with an
					artist's fervour and concentration to produce a masterpiece.” With her
					permission, <persName key="Margaret Oliphant" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A9308c943-ac98-4296-bd0d-03e4149578fa">Oliphant’s</persName> cousin Annie Cogshil published her autobiography
					posthumously for the financial benefit of her nieces. More controversially,
						<persName key="Annie Besant" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3A0ac4cb65-38a5-49d5-a31a-5c15d3cfb669">Annie Besant’s</persName>
					<title level="m">An Autobiography</title> (1884) traces her shifts in belief, as
					she goes from Christian to atheist to Theosophist. She was also an ardent
					supporter of birth control. Explaining her life’s mission, she wrote: “I ask no
					other epitaph on my tomb but SHE TRIED TO FOLLOW TRUTH”. Ten years before her
					death, <persName key="Frances Power Cobbe" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Afd48b526-e932-43d3-94c6-19cad1640b09">Cobbe</persName> published the <title level="m">Life of Frances Power Cobbe
						by Herself </title>(1894), in order to show that single women could lead
					fulfilling lives. (<persName key="Frances Power Cobbe" ref="https://cwrc.ca/islandora/object/orlando%3Afd48b526-e932-43d3-94c6-19cad1640b09">Cobbe</persName> was in fact a partnered lesbian but this was not explicit
					in her text.) In the twentieth century, the left-wing intellectual Beatrice
					Webb, published <title level="m">My Apprenticeship</title> (1926), detailing her
					life before her marriage and intellectual partnership with Sidney Webb, with
					whom she wrote more than a dozen books. Two years before her death, popular
					novelist Mary Augusta Ward published <title level="m">A Writer’s
						Recollections</title> (1918).<title level="m"> A Writer’s
						Recollection</title> follows the memoir format of thirty years earlier,
					focusing not on Ward’s interior drama, but instead sharing anecdotes about
					writers who happen to be family members (Matthew Arnold was her uncle), and
					showing the genesis of her writing in family life.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="subsection">
				<head>Conclusion</head>
				<p>Life writing presented both challenges and opportunities for women writers. On
					the one hand, “autobiography” was the third most common genre that women writers
					published. Furthermore, private letters and diaries were part of everyday life,
					and blended seamlessly with women’s duties as family record-keepers and
					archivists. These letters and diaries were generally never intended for
					publication, and if they saw print it was generally in the twentieth century,
					many decades after the death of their authors. Women writers did complete the
					memoirs of male relatives, and short autobiographical and biographical prefaces
					were not unusual. What was more unusual was a woman writer completing a
					monograph-length biography of another woman or an autobiography of herself with
					an intent to publish it, as Gaskell and Martineau did. Instead, manywomen
					developed new forms of writing, including collective biography and memoir, which
					drew out networks of many people and relationships. Many more women writers
					contributed to the development of relational models of the self in the
					collective biography, which considered multiple subjects under one cover, and
					the memoir, which decentered the writer, who reported on the literary and
					artistic milieu of her youth rather than on herself. The collective biography,
					the memoir, and the family biography of a husband or father all authorised women
					to put lives in print in part by decentering the writer and presenting a
					relational rather than an individual model of the self. In the final decade of
					the nineteenth century and the early decades of the twentieth century, women
					writers wrote autobiography in greater numbers than before, merging elements of
					the domestic novel with new stories of women’s professional careers. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="notes">
				<head>Notes</head>
				<note n="1" type="scholarlyNote">The poem has a suggestion of the magical imagery of
					Kenneth Leslie?s By Stubborn Stars.</note>
				<note n="2" type="scholarlyNote">The <title ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/179269842" level="m">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title> argues the author
					did not publish this text before<date cert="high" when="1934">1934</date>.</note>
				<note n="3" type="scholarlyNote">Sample footnote.</note>
			</div>
			<div type="annotations">
				<head>Annotations and Keywords</head>
				<note type="researchNote">These annotations can be added to the prose content or in
					a separate section</note>
				<note type="link">Poem featured in <ref target="http://cufts2.lib.sfu.ca/CRDB4/BVAS/resource/5724">Canada's Early
						Women Writers</ref>
				</note>
				<note type="keyword">Sample annotation</note>
				<note type="correction">Sample correction</note>
				<note type="indexTerm">Sample index term</note>
				<note type="translation">Sample translation</note>
			</div>
			<div type="works">
				<head>
					<choice>
						<sic> Works Cited </sic>
						<corr>Bibliography</corr>
					</choice>
				</head>
				<note>The New Monthly Magazine. Alternate Titles: The New Monthly Magazine and
					Universal Register; The New Monthly Magazine and Literary Journal; Colburn's New
					Monthly Magazine; The New Monthly Magazine and Humorist.London:H.
						Colburn;<orgName cert="medium" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/151283596">Chapman
						and Hall</orgName>;John Bale and Sons,1814-1884.</note>
				<note>Sample bibliographic record: <persName cert="high" type="real" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/78272387">McLaren, Floris Clark</persName>.
					Glimpse. Canadian Poetry Magazine1.1(1936):23.</note>
				<note>Sample bibliographic record: McLaren, Floris Clark. Glimpse. Canadian Poetry
					Magazine1.1(1936):23.Volume I: 1450-1625, Volume II: 1625-1700, Volume III:
					1700-1800, Volume IV: 1800-1900, Volume V: Indexes of Titles, First Lines,
					Names, Repositories</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>